<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>David L. Day</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/</link><description>Recent content on David L. Day</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.davidlday.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Bibliography</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/bibliography/</link><pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/bibliography/</guid><description>Books Tearstone (Kindle or Paperback) - Dark Recesses Press, March 2018 Miscalculations - No longer available. Rutledge Books, 1995. Yes, it’s on Amazon, and someone thinks they can sell a copy for $45. Don’t buy it. I’ll be republishing it sometime. Short Stories &amp;ldquo;The Infernal Gift&amp;rdquo; - That Which Cannot Be Undone, October 2022 &amp;ldquo;Defend Atlantis&amp;rdquo; - Terror Politico, January 2019 &amp;ldquo;Vacation&amp;rdquo; - Aurora Wolf, October 2018 &amp;ldquo;Black Hand&amp;rdquo; - Double Feature Magazine, #1 October 2016 &amp;ldquo;A Gathering of Lost Shadows&amp;rdquo; - Hazard Yet Forward August 2012 &amp;ldquo;Gray&amp;rdquo; - Necrotic Tissue, #5 January 2009</description></item><item><title>A White Box</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2018/04/17/white-box/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2018/04/17/white-box/</guid><description>“Our memory is a more perfect world than the universe: it gives back life to those who no longer exist.”
~ Guy de Maupassant
I have a picture of you from 1971.
You are dressed in a white sleeveless top and matching white stockings kneeling next to a tree. Nestled in your arms is a small, white bundle with a tuft of dark hair. Your face is turned down, but not so much that your proud, slight smile is hidden.</description></item><item><title>David’s Writer Bio</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/about/</link><pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/about/</guid><description>Short Bio David Day believes the future is a paradox, simultaneously representing beautiful hope and terrible possibility, and that we are on an ever-constant journey to resolve that paradox into the now. David received his MA in Writing Popular Fiction from Seton Hill University in June 2011. He is the author of one novel, Tearstone, as well as several short stories.
A Little More… I write dark fantasy, often with a heavy helping of religious symbolism.</description></item><item><title>Saying Goodbye to Our Dog</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2016/03/26/goodbye-zoe/</link><pubDate>Sat, 26 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2016/03/26/goodbye-zoe/</guid><description>&amp;ldquo;Until one has loved an animal, a part of one&amp;rsquo;s soul remains unawakened.&amp;rdquo;
~ Anatole France
Our kitchen table is back in the kitchen. The screen door on our back porch stays closed. I don&amp;rsquo;t scurry downstairs to turn off the alarm in the wee hours of the morning. Things are back to normal.
Except they aren&amp;rsquo;t. They never will be.
We incrementally changed our lives to accommodate our aging dog Zoe, which was at times frustrating for all of us, but never burden.</description></item><item><title>Diversity in the Reading List</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2016/03/08/diversity-in-reading/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2016/03/08/diversity-in-reading/</guid><description>Happy International Women&amp;rsquo;s Day!
In honor of, I&amp;rsquo;d like to share my reading list from 2015. Except for 2 non-fiction books I read for work, all of these works were written by women authors. Take a quick look:
You by Caroline Kepnes Fuse by Julianna Baggott Burn by Julianna Baggott A Discovery of Witches by Deborah Harkness Over Sea, Under Stone by Susan Cooper The Dark is Rising by Susan Cooper Shadow of Night by Deborah Harkness Greenwitch by Susan Cooper The Cognitive Style of Power Point by Edward R.</description></item><item><title>The Accidental Non-Smoker</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2016/02/20/i-quit-smoking/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2016/02/20/i-quit-smoking/</guid><description>I quit smoking this year (yes, even the electronic ones), and like so many of the positive things in my life, this was a complete accident. My last cigarrette was on December 31, 2015. I&amp;rsquo;ve even kept the pack, which is still half full. I don&amp;rsquo;t give it a second thought.
I love nicotine almost as much as I love caffeine. I&amp;rsquo;m something of a stimulant junkie (as much as the law will allow) I think in part because my natural state of being is so low key and laid back that I&amp;rsquo;m something like half-a-step behind the rest of the world, out of phase.</description></item><item><title>Getting Back Into It</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2016/01/10/getting-back-into-it/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2016/01/10/getting-back-into-it/</guid><description>Nearly four years ago, in early 2012, I started taking Taekwondo. I was overweight, out of shape, but my oldest minion had been taking classes for a year plus and had just turned old enough to start doing family classes. So I buckled down, drank plenty of water, tried not to smoke so much and gave it a shot.
I didn&amp;rsquo;t just show up to class with him one day, though.</description></item><item><title>Interviews</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/interviews/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/interviews/</guid><description>Thoughts I&amp;rsquo;ve shared with others around the web. If you&amp;rsquo;d like to interview me for your website, drop me a note or ping me through one of my social channels. I&amp;rsquo;m more than happy to do interviews via email.
2014-08-06: SF Signal Mind Meld: Wherein I reveal what Bill Cosby and Arch Oboler have in common. 2013-06-02: Eclipse Spotlight with Meg Mims: Wherein I confess to drinking both coffee and tea.</description></item><item><title>Reviews</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/reviews/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/reviews/</guid><description>Interested in learning what others think of my work? Me too. If you&amp;rsquo;ve posted an online review of my work I&amp;rsquo;d love to add a link to it here. Five stars or one star (or even no stars), drop me an email with a URL, and I&amp;rsquo;ll add a link.
Tearstone 2014-08-29: The Horror Bookshelf 2013-10-17: Geekdom of Gore 2013-07-14: Nameless Magazine 2013-06-24: Horror Novel Reviews 2013-04-17: GMTA Literary Community Customer Reviews on Amazon Community Reviews on Goodreads</description></item><item><title>Short Story Structure</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2013/01/07/short-story-structure/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Jan 2013 06:30:07 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2013/01/07/short-story-structure/</guid><description>I wrapped up a first draft of my next novel in early December, and I decided to make 2013 a year for building my short story skills. I love short stories, but I’m more inclined toward novels and long fiction, I think in part because they’re, well, longer. I like robust stories with full worlds and deep characters.
I write 3-4 shorts a year, which isn’t a lot, and they reflect my inclination toward longer stories.</description></item><item><title>Reading List for 2012</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2013/01/04/reading-list-for-2012/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2013 09:12:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2013/01/04/reading-list-for-2012/</guid><description>Following the lead of Chris Shearer and Heidi Ruby Miller, I’m sharing my reading list from 2012.
My goal was 40 books, and I came in just over at 41. Some of my favorites were Never Let Me Go by Kazuo Ishiguro, John Dies at the End by David Wong, Westlake Soul by Rio Youers, The Passage by Justin Cronin, and The Croning by Laird Barron.
My 2012 reading list in alphabetical order:</description></item><item><title>The Next Big Thing</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/12/17/the-next-big-thing/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 Dec 2012 05:58:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/12/17/the-next-big-thing/</guid><description>Sheldon Higdon asked if I’d do this “Next Big Thing” blog chain. I’m not particularly keen on this sort of thing, mainly because my work is so volatile right up until it goes out the door, but Sheldon’s a good friend, and my last post on this project was somewhat cryptic. So I thought I would follow-up with something a little less vague. This is my next novel-length project. Whether it turns out to be any kind of “Big Thing” remains to be seen.</description></item><item><title>The Duotrope Question</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/12/14/the-duotrope-question/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Dec 2012 05:57:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/12/14/the-duotrope-question/</guid><description>Over the past couple of weeks writers have been debating the wisdom of Duotrope’s decision to start charging for their service. The site’s been around for years and has relied solely on donations to keep it running. And apparently donations were not enough.
Like so many others, I’ve been considering what to do come 2013. I’ve donated to the site a few times, giving what I felt was a fair price for the service on a yearly basis.</description></item><item><title>Tearstone Update - Dec 2012</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/12/10/tearstone-update-dec-2012/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Dec 2012 05:13:31 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/12/10/tearstone-update-dec-2012/</guid><description>Here’s a quick updated on Tearstone. The manuscript is now in the hands of Tracy DeVore, Senior Editor for Belfire Press. Tracy’s a published author, freelance editor, and former newspaper correspondent. She was also founding president of the Horror Writers Association’s Indiana chapter, and I feel lucky to be working with her.
The front cover art will be handled by Bob Freeman. No ETA on it yet, but I’ll share updates as I’m able.</description></item><item><title>Tumblr with iA Writer</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/12/07/tumblr-with-ia-writer/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Dec 2012 17:27:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/12/07/tumblr-with-ia-writer/</guid><description>It’s been a while since I’ve posted. I’d like to say there’s somereally good reason I don’t post frequently, but I’d be lying. Fact is,I’m just not much for jumping into my browser to write anything. Oneof my [recent posts]({% post_url 2012-10-20-look-ma-no-word-processor %}) dealt with abandoning my word processor for something better suitedfor drafting a novel. In that case, I settled on using IndexCard. It’s relatively distraction free, lets me work in a non-linear fashion, and works onthe iPad.</description></item><item><title>Sweet Baby Cthulhu! I've Been Infected!</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/10/23/sweet-baby-cthulhu-ive-been-infected/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2012 22:46:32 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/10/23/sweet-baby-cthulhu-ive-been-infected/</guid><description>The hip and talented writer Stephanie Wytovich tagged me in a game of author infection. The rules are simple. Search your work in progress for the first use of “look”. Copy and paste that paragraph and the ones immediately before and after into a blog post. Then, like all good chain letters, tag five other authors. Wash, rinse, repeat.
This is from the nearly finished first draft of my novel The Galvanized Man.</description></item><item><title>Look, Ma, No Word Processor!</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/10/20/look-ma-no-word-processor/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Oct 2012 10:15:05 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/10/20/look-ma-no-word-processor/</guid><description>A couple of weeks ago I posted about how I needed to get back to planning. My current project—a novel that’s probably too complex, but fun to write—stalled and I couldn’t find a way back into the story. I needed to put the word processor aside and revisit the fundamental structure of the story.
I also mentioned in that post how I like to use index cards for planning my DIY projects around the house.</description></item><item><title>No More Sleepy Posts</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/10/11/no-more-sleepy-posts/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2012 06:05:55 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/10/11/no-more-sleepy-posts/</guid><description>Just a quick announcement I no longer plan to blog regularly about my polyphasic sleep. I have a few different reasons, but the biggest is that frankly I don’t think my personal experiment is all that interesting. I’m still interested, but I can’t get all that excited about it. My sleep data goes back to the middle of July, and what I noticed is that even when I sleep in, I usually only sleep about six hours.</description></item><item><title>A Little Bit of Planning...</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/10/08/a-little-bit-of-planning/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2012 04:59:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/10/08/a-little-bit-of-planning/</guid><description>I had an epiphany yesterday while working on a “weekend project” that’s taken several months. You see, there are no more real weekend projects in our home since we had our second son. My wife and I are lucky to get five minutes to ourselves on any given day, which is more than fine since we love our boys and love hanging out with them. But it sure makes it tough to indulge our DIY tendencies.</description></item><item><title>Sleeping Like an Idiot: Week 7 - Charts!</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/09/24/sleeping-like-an-idiot-week-7-charts/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2012 03:33:40 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/09/24/sleeping-like-an-idiot-week-7-charts/</guid><description>I managed to pull together four charts to help demonstrate progress. I took a cue from The Hacker’s Diet and used a 20-Day moving average to get trends. In each chart the actual measure is in blue and the trend is in orange. For now I just used a Simple Moving Average since the charts are just to get a sense of how things are going and aren’t meant to give highly accurate measures.</description></item><item><title>Sleep Experiment: Week 6</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/09/18/sleep-experiment-week-6/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Sep 2012 07:28:56 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/09/18/sleep-experiment-week-6/</guid><description>I’m a couple of days behind in putting this up, mainly because I was hoping to get some charts put together from my Zeo. The charts provided through its software are nice, but they’re not really showing what I want, so I have a little bit of work to do still.
Remember, I’m doing an Everyman sleep schedule, which involves a major sleep event at night and multiple naps during the day.</description></item><item><title>Reintroducing the Sleep Experiment: 5 Weeks @ 5 Hours a Night</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/09/09/reintroducing-the-sleep-experiment-5-weeks-5/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2012 08:42:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/09/09/reintroducing-the-sleep-experiment-5-weeks-5/</guid><description>About five weeks ago I posted about the sleep experiment I was undertaking. I haven’t been as diligent as I would like in recording results via blog, so I’m going to do some catching up here and make the effort more frequently.
Yesterday I caught up on the progress of Handy Andy Pandy—this dude’s an inspiration for me. I also reread my [first post]({% post_url 2012-07-21-a-writers-experiment-with-sleep %}) and realized it didn’t actually share details on what I’m doing very well.</description></item><item><title>Why Book Reviews Suck And How We Can Fix Them</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/08/31/why-book-reviews-suck-and-how-we-can-fix-them/</link><pubDate>Fri, 31 Aug 2012 06:30:18 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/08/31/why-book-reviews-suck-and-how-we-can-fix-them/</guid><description>Disclaimer: This post comes from me as a technologist and a reader, not as a writer. As a writer, I keep my opinions on reviews and reviewers to myself.
All the recent exposure on GettingBookReviews.com and John Locke’s lack of disclosure on using the service prompted me to finally put up a post on something I’ve been thinking about for a while.
Paying someone to review your book is like asking your mom what she thought of the card you made her for Mother’s Day in the third grade.</description></item><item><title>How to Succeed as a Writer</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/08/10/how-to-succeed-as-a-writer/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Aug 2012 06:45:51 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/08/10/how-to-succeed-as-a-writer/</guid><description>A couple of days ago, Jeff VanderMeer posted an articulate and insightful piece on the future of publishing. It’s not typical among the current flood of posts and opinions about where we’re going or what the next hot thing is. Rather, Jeff gets to the heart of what he believes to be a real problem today with the advice and predictions being touted in the writing community.
Go read his post if you haven’t already.</description></item><item><title>Charity Anthology Released</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/08/08/charity-anthology-released/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Aug 2012 05:39:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/08/08/charity-anthology-released/</guid><description>Yesterday marked the release of Hazard Yet Forward, a charity anthology composed of stories by seventy-six writers connected to the Seton Hill University Writing Popular Fiction program. The anthology was compiled in support of Donna Munro, an 2004 graduate of the program. Find out more details at the HYF website, and check out the Amazon page. There was a lot of buzz on Facebook and Twitter (still going even this morning, I believe), and the anthology quickly rose among Amazon’s Hot New Releases to crest at #1 in Short Story Anthologies yesterday afternoon.</description></item><item><title>You see a mousetrap;
I see free cheese and a fucking challenge!</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/07/25/you-see-a-mousetrap-i-see-free-cheese-and-a/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Jul 2012 21:19:17 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/07/25/you-see-a-mousetrap-i-see-free-cheese-and-a/</guid><description>You see a mousetrap; I see free cheese and a fucking challenge!— Scroobius Pip</description></item><item><title>A Writer's Experiment with Sleep</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/07/21/a-writers-experiment-with-sleep/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Jul 2012 16:56:04 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/07/21/a-writers-experiment-with-sleep/</guid><description>Last week I started a new experiment in writing, one that I hope will both boost productivity and creativity. It’s not your typical experiment, though. I’m not going to stand on my head while I write, or use prompt cards, or any other fancy tools I don’t already use. I’m going to change something much more fundamental about my writing habit. I’m changing my sleep. Okay, not so exciting, but I think it’s a promising approach.</description></item><item><title>WHERE WOULD YOU MOST LIKE TO VISIT ON YOUR PLANET?</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/07/17/where-would-you-most-like-to-visit-on-your-planet/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Jul 2012 09:52:54 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/07/17/where-would-you-most-like-to-visit-on-your-planet/</guid><description>Antarctica, a place of utter isolation and desolation. It is by far the most unearthly place on earth. And it always makes me think of H.P. Lovecraft. Always.</description></item><item><title>Goodbye WordPress</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/03/04/goodbye-wordpress/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/03/04/goodbye-wordpress/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;m done with WordPress. It&amp;rsquo;s wonderful, but it&amp;rsquo;s too much for me. I know in this day and age it seems every aspiring writer runs a tight blog, with frequent posts and guests and insightful advice on writing. But that&amp;rsquo;s not for me.
I spent too much time over the past few years tweaking and tuning WordPress, not enough time actually writing posts, and beating myself up over both. So I&amp;rsquo;m ditching the pretense that I&amp;rsquo;m a blogger.</description></item><item><title>Time for a Change</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2011/07/06/time-for-a-change/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2011/07/06/time-for-a-change/</guid><description>For the past two years, I used this blog to publish most of my reading journals for my graduate program. I graduated in June, and now it&amp;rsquo;s time to give this place a new purpose.
I&amp;rsquo;ve put a lot of thought into what kind of thing this site should morph into, and I haven&amp;rsquo;t quite decided yet. I think I&amp;rsquo;ll start doing book reviews, but we&amp;rsquo;ll see. For now, I&amp;rsquo;ll post the occasional thought and progress as I work toward publication.</description></item><item><title>Scrivener for Windows… and Linux?</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/11/25/scrivener-for-windows-and-linux/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/11/25/scrivener-for-windows-and-linux/</guid><description>There are some interesting things going on at Literature &amp;amp; Latte. First, they&amp;rsquo;ve released a Windows Beta version of their unique and popular writing software Scrivener, which isn&amp;rsquo;t really news. However, what doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem well-known yet is that on their message boards, a group of folks is playing with an unofficial version for Linux.
If you&amp;rsquo;re really interested in using Scrivener, I urge you to sign up for the Windows Beta and try it out.</description></item><item><title>Thoughts on The Exorcist by William Peter Blatty</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/10/17/thoughts-on-the-exorcist-by-william-peter-blatty/</link><pubDate>Sun, 17 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/10/17/thoughts-on-the-exorcist-by-william-peter-blatty/</guid><description>Most people should be familiar with Blatty&amp;rsquo;s The Exorcist by now. I mean, it&amp;rsquo;s a classic, right? The mere mention of the title suggests Linda Blair spewing ungodly amounts of pea soup. So no introduction is necessary. It is definitely a great horror novel that everyone with even a minor interest in horror should read. Go read it. Now. I mean it.
Okay, all due praise aside, there are two things about the novel that stood out for me as a writer.</description></item><item><title>Thoughts on Ansen Dibell’s “Plot”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/09/28/thoughts-on-ansen-dibells-plot/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/09/28/thoughts-on-ansen-dibells-plot/</guid><description>One of the most challenging things I struggle with as both a writer of fiction and a student of literature (yeah, they always go together) is which tool to use when. I believe that while reading and writing are intricately related&amp;ndash;you must be well-read to be well-written&amp;ndash;they don&amp;rsquo;t use the same mental tools.
The term plot (my archenemy when it comes to writing) appears in both toolkits, and I think that is terribly confusing.</description></item><item><title>Thoughts on Nate Kenyon’s “Sparrow Rock”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/08/24/thoughts-on-nate-kenyons-sparrow-rock/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/08/24/thoughts-on-nate-kenyons-sparrow-rock/</guid><description>I just finished reading Nate Kenyon&amp;rsquo;s latest novel, Sparrow Rock, a story of a group of high school kids who find themselves trapped in a bomb shelter by accident just as the end of the world arrives. Read the official synopsis from Nate&amp;rsquo;s site.
The novel has received excellent reviews at multiple sites, and I think the praise is well-deserved. Kenyon has produced a fast-paced, engaging tale of survival. This is the second book I&amp;rsquo;ve read by Kenyon.</description></item><item><title>Thoughts on Bently Little’s “The Town”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/08/08/thoughts-on-bently-littles-the-town/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/08/08/thoughts-on-bently-littles-the-town/</guid><description>Bently Little&amp;rsquo;s The Town was published in 2000, and I think even 10 years later it holds up as a good story. I found Bently&amp;rsquo;s take on small-town horror refreshing in many ways, even though the idea of horror in a small town isn&amp;rsquo;t so unique by today&amp;rsquo;s standards. The story involves a family of six who move back to the father&amp;rsquo;s home town after winning the lottery to simplify their lives and exchange the dangers of LA for the assumed tranquility of McGuane, Arizona.</description></item><item><title>Why Character Matters</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/07/05/why-character-matters/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/07/05/why-character-matters/</guid><description>I just finished reading Edward Lee&amp;rsquo;s The Golem. This is my first encounter with any of Edward Lee&amp;rsquo;s work. I believe every author should have two chances, so Ed Lee has one left. To me, the book read like a first draft, but I&amp;rsquo;ll get to that.
We don&amp;rsquo;t see the golem used much in popular fiction. I can only recall one instance where I&amp;rsquo;ve seen it used&amp;ndash;an old episode of the X-Files called Kaddish.</description></item><item><title>Manuscript Templates</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/06/09/manuscript-templates/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/06/09/manuscript-templates/</guid><description>Part of being a professional writer is ensuring your submissions meet format guidelines. William Shunn developed a set of format guidelines, originally published in December 1998 edition of Writers Write: The Internet Writing Journal. He also provides a set of templates on his site, but unfortunately they are only for WordPerfect. I use OpenOffice.
I decided to create my own templates based on his guidelines and offer them here for all to use.</description></item><item><title>One Helluva Ghost Story</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/04/27/one-helluva-ghost-story/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/04/27/one-helluva-ghost-story/</guid><description>I just finished reading Tom Piccirilli&amp;rsquo;s A Choir of Ill Children&amp;ndash;for the second time. I read it back in February and decided that to do it any justice, I needed to set it aside and reread it. It&amp;rsquo;s not an overly complex book, but I&amp;rsquo;m not used to the Southern style. The last book I read that felt stylistically similar was Faulkner&amp;rsquo;s As I Lay Dying&amp;ndash;over fifteen years ago.
The first thing that I noticed is the uniqueness of every character.</description></item><item><title>Another Round of How-To, Part 3</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/04/07/another-round-of-how-to-part-3/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/04/07/another-round-of-how-to-part-3/</guid><description>This is the last of a three-part journal on How to Write Tales of Horror, Fantasy &amp;amp; Science Fiction, Edited by J. N. Williamson, a collection of How-To articles by some of the best horror writers, circa 1987. Part one covered chapters 1-8; part two covered chapters 9-18.
The advice found in these final chapters still mirrors advice found in the wonderful On Writing Horror, another collection of How-To articles by some of horror&amp;rsquo;s best writers circa 2007.</description></item><item><title>Another Round of How-To, Part 2</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/03/23/another-round-of-how-to-part-2/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/03/23/another-round-of-how-to-part-2/</guid><description>This is part two of a three-part journal on How to Write Tales of Horror, Fantasy &amp;amp; Science Fiction, Edited by J. N. Williamson, a collection of How-To articles by some of the best horror writers, circa 1987. Part one covered chapters 1-8.
In my first post, I mentioned how strikingly similar the advice is to that found in On Writing Horror, another collection of How-To articles by some of horror&amp;rsquo;s best writers circa 2007.</description></item><item><title>Another Round of How-To</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/03/01/another-round-of-how-to/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/03/01/another-round-of-how-to/</guid><description>This is the first of three posts on How to Write Tales of Horror, Fantasy &amp;amp; Science Fiction, Edited by J. N. Williamson. The book is a collection of How-To articles by some of the best horror writers, circa 1987.
Late last year I did a series of posts on On Writing Horror, another collection of How-To articles by some of horror&amp;rsquo;s best writers circa 2007. Twenty years separate the publication of these two books, but so far I haven&amp;rsquo;t found anything other than the market survey that really differentiate the two.</description></item><item><title>Measuring Quality – Words or Pages</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/01/31/measuring-quality-words-or-pages/</link><pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/01/31/measuring-quality-words-or-pages/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;m a couple of weeks into my second term in Seton Hill&amp;rsquo;s MA WPF program. My thesis is a marketable horror novel, targeted at 350 pages. My personal goal is to complete the 1st draft by the end of this term, and spend the rest of my program editing and revision. Or rewriting if my mentors so command.
None of that is particularly interesting, but they&amp;rsquo;re facts that lay the groundwork for what&amp;rsquo;s been on my mind lately.</description></item><item><title>Back to work...</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/01/08/back-to-work/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/01/08/back-to-work/</guid><description>Just got back from residency orientation @ Seton Hill. It&amp;rsquo;s nice to be back, even if it meant driving 4 hours through snow. I had a great break, had a couple of good reads while I was off. First was John Scalzi&amp;rsquo;s Old Man&amp;rsquo;s War, a very entertaining science fiction book. It&amp;rsquo;s not my typical flavor, but it kept me reading, full of good action and interesting characters.
My other read was The Mammoth Book of Best New Horror, Volume 20, edited by Stephen Jones.</description></item><item><title>A Bit of a Break</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/12/01/a-bit-of-a-break/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/12/01/a-bit-of-a-break/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been on break from school since beginning of November, so I took the opportunity to brush up on mechanics. Specifically, I took a much-needed browse through the old Elements of Style. Good little book. But, I wanted more. So, I found a more contemporary take on style, Sin and Syntax, by Constance Hale. It&amp;rsquo;s longer than Elements. There&amp;rsquo;s plenty of praise for the book out in the wild; I&amp;rsquo;ll say I&amp;rsquo;m glad I took the time to read it as well.</description></item><item><title>Down to Business</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/21/down-to-business/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/21/down-to-business/</guid><description>In the end, writing is like any other endeavor. Sure, there is a significant and compelling creative aspect to it, almost mystical at times. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t just happen, though. The magic comes through sweat and rigor. King lays this out in his final section of On Writing.
His opinion is that there are 4 classes of writer: Bad, Competent, Good, and Genius. He states that there are 2 theses to his book:</description></item><item><title>Tools of the Trade</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/18/tools-of-the-trade/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/18/tools-of-the-trade/</guid><description>In part two of On Writing, King gives an overview of what he considers the essential tools for every writer&amp;rsquo;s toolbox. The analogy is interesting, and the story he provides at the start demonstrates an excellent point: Always have all your tools with you so you can tackle any unexpected situation.
So what goes in this metaphorical toolbox?
The first layer consists of common tools. The most common tool, per King, is vocabulary.</description></item><item><title>A Fogged-Out Landscape</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/17/a-fogged-out-landscape/</link><pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/17/a-fogged-out-landscape/</guid><description>It&amp;rsquo;s wonderful how much we can learn from stories, particularly when well told. Stephen King spends the first part of his book, On Writing, by walking the reader through a series of &amp;lsquo;fogged-out&amp;rsquo; memories. The book itself is about writing. But he sets the stage by doing what he does best, and tells the story of what made him what he is today.
I can&amp;rsquo;t say if it was intentional on his part, but in telling what he considers his &amp;ldquo;C.</description></item><item><title>“On Writing… oh, to hell with it.</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/15/on-writing-oh-to-hell-with-it/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2009 02:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/15/on-writing-oh-to-hell-with-it/</guid><description>The last section of &amp;ldquo;On Writing Horror&amp;rdquo; is all about the business aspect of being a writer. It provides a nice overview of the current markets, good resources for research and promotion, and some worthwhile advice from editors and writers alike.
Here&amp;rsquo;s the advice I&amp;rsquo;m taking right now, given by Night Shade Books:
Write what you think is your best book. Put it in a trunk and write another one. Do this four times.</description></item><item><title>“On Writing Horror” – Part Seven</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/15/on-writing-horror-part-7/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2009 00:01:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/15/on-writing-horror-part-7/</guid><description>Part 7 of On Writing Horror is titled &amp;ldquo;Genre and Subgenre&amp;rdquo;, but the 10 articles also cover concerns with medium as well (screenplay, theater, audio).
Archetypes and Fearful Allure: Writing Erotic Horror, Nancy Kilpatrick
I really struggled with this one. Kilpatrick seems to rely heavily on the concept of Archetypes, and the crux of her advice can be summed up in the following quote:
This means that the energy embedded in the image resonates with all readers because it taps into and stirs up the collective unconscious.</description></item><item><title>“On Writing Horror” – Part Six</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/11/on-writing-horror-part-six/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/11/on-writing-horror-part-six/</guid><description>Part 6 of On Writing Horror is titled &amp;ldquo;Tradition and Modern Times&amp;rdquo;, a series of articles covering horror tradition and its place in our modern literature.
No More Silver Mirrors: The Monster in Our Times, Karen E. Taylor
Taylor addresses how the old monsters can be made new again. She&amp;rsquo;s got some good advice, and I&amp;rsquo;ll get to that in a second, but there&amp;rsquo;s something she says early on that is direct opposition to what at least one other author claims in this series of articles.</description></item><item><title>“On Writing Horror” – Part Five</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/09/on-writing-horror-part-five/</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/09/on-writing-horror-part-five/</guid><description>Part 5 of On Writing Horror is titled &amp;ldquo;Horror, Art, Innovation, Excellence&amp;rdquo;. Five articles. Actually, 4 articles and one interesting interview with Harlan Ellison.
Innovation in Horror, Jeanne Cavelos
I&amp;rsquo;m starting to see patterns of advice in these articles, even though they have different emphasis. Cavelos talks in terms of innovation, but starts with the foundational advice of read a lot, read both in and out of the genre. Doing so helps the amateur writer avoid writing something that&amp;rsquo;s old under the false belief that they&amp;rsquo;ve written something new.</description></item><item><title>“On Writing Horror” – Part Four</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/07/on-writing-horror-part-four/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/07/on-writing-horror-part-four/</guid><description>Part 4 of On Writing Horror is titled &amp;ldquo;Horror Crafting&amp;rdquo;, and encompasses 7 articles on the craft. So many articles, and much of it is advice I&amp;rsquo;ve heard before, so I&amp;rsquo;m going to keep this as short as I can.
Such Horrible People, Tina Jens
Per Jens, &amp;ldquo;Horror is about how people react when they encounter the plot.&amp;rdquo; So to have good horror, we need good characters who interact with the plot.</description></item><item><title>“On Writing Horror” – Part Three</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/04/on-writing-horror-part-three/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/04/on-writing-horror-part-three/</guid><description>Part 3 of On Writing Horror is titled &amp;ldquo;Developing Horror Concepts&amp;rdquo;. It contains four articles dealing with conceiving and developing ideas for horror.
A World of Dark and Disturbing Ideas, J. N. Williamson
Williamson chooses to speak in terms of &amp;ldquo;useful premise&amp;rdquo; as opposed to &amp;ldquo;idea&amp;rdquo;, and I can appreciate his working definition. Idea&amp;rsquo;s are great, but they are largely useless if they cannot or will not be executed. This is true pretty much regardless of profession or circumstance.</description></item><item><title>“On Writing Horror” – Part Two</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/03/on-writing-horror-part-two/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/03/on-writing-horror-part-two/</guid><description>Part 2 of On Writing Horror, titled &amp;ldquo;An Education in Horror&amp;rdquo;, briefly addresses a horror writer&amp;rsquo;s education in four articles.
What You Are Meant to Know: Twenty-One Horror Classics, Robert Weinberg
Weinberg&amp;rsquo;s message is pretty clear - know your genre. He suggests that, in order to be marketable, you must be original. And, in order to be original, you must know what&amp;rsquo;s already been done. Aside from the mechanics of writing, a horror writer must be familiar with what&amp;rsquo;s been done.</description></item><item><title>“On Writing Horror” – Part One</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/01/on-writing-horror-part-one/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/01/on-writing-horror-part-one/</guid><description>Today I&amp;rsquo;m starting my journal entries for On Writing Horror, A Handbook by The Horror Writer&amp;rsquo;s Association. The book contains about 50 individual articles, divided among 8 different sections, so I&amp;rsquo;m going to match my entries up to the sections rather than address the articles individually.
Part one is called &amp;ldquo;Horror, Literature, and Horror Literature&amp;rdquo;. The three articles in this section seem to address whether Horror Fiction is or isn&amp;rsquo;t Literary Fiction.</description></item><item><title>“Urban Gothic” – No Signal</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/29/urban-gothic-no-signal/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/29/urban-gothic-no-signal/</guid><description>Screenwriter John August has an interesting little post on cell phones in the movies. It includes a great little montage of movie clips showing phones not working, getting smashed, etc. Why on earth do I care?
Brian Keene has this very problem in Urban Gothic. In an era where it seems everyone has a cell phone, how does a writer deal with it?
By my count, there are six teenagers in Keene&amp;rsquo;s book, each of whom has their own cell phone.</description></item><item><title>“Urban Gothic” and The Minotaur</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/24/urban-gothic-and-the-minotaur/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2009 00:02:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/24/urban-gothic-and-the-minotaur/</guid><description>Brian Keene’s recently released Urban Gothic brought to mind the myth of the Minotaur. A group of teens is thrown into a labyrinthine house whose twists and turns extend far below the ground in a neglected neighborhood. Their first encounter is with a hulking, deformed creature whose strength seems insurmountable.
Keene tells this story from multiple points of view, and I think that worked really well for the fast-paced action. I noticed, too, that Keene give the reader an immediate indication of POV change by having the POV character identified, in most cases, in the first sentence of any section change.</description></item><item><title>“Stephen King&amp;#58; The Art of Darkness” - Night Journey</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/24/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-night-journey/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2009 00:01:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/24/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-night-journey/</guid><description>What is the “night journey” in the context of Stephen King?
First, Winter shows how all of King’s works deal with some sort of journey. The idea of story as a journey is not new. Joseph Campbell is well known for his “Hero’s Journey”, and I’ve often encountered the aphorism that “the main character must change” (which is essentially an internal journey - A to B).
What I find most interesting is how Winter chooses to discuss the idea of journey in King’s works.</description></item><item><title>“Stephen King&amp;#58; The Art of Darkness” – Change of Approach</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/16/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-change-of-approach/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/16/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-change-of-approach/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;m scrapping the chapter-by-chapter approach for my discussion on Douglas Winter&amp;rsquo;s book.
Instead, I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to do a series of posts, each of which discusses what I found to be the most critical and relevant elements in Winter&amp;rsquo;s analysis. Here&amp;rsquo;s a list of topics I expect to cover. I&amp;rsquo;ll be spending no more than 30 minutes on any given element to keep myself from rambling on.
The &amp;ldquo;Night Journey&amp;rdquo; (East to West) The Haunted House Character growth from innocence to experience (tied to the &amp;ldquo;Night Journey&amp;rdquo;) The corruption of Fairy Tale Vision and the writing process That said, look for my first post in the next day or so.</description></item><item><title>“Stephen King&amp;#58; The Art of Darkness” (Ch. 3 – 4)</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/08/05/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-ch-3-4/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/08/05/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-ch-3-4/</guid><description>Chapter 3 - Carrie
In chapter 3, Winter begins his critical analysis of King&amp;rsquo;s work with Carrie.
Here&amp;rsquo;s what I took from this chapter:
Winter considers Carrie to be King&amp;rsquo;s most eccentric work. In part, it seems, due to the epistolary structure. Right from the start, King&amp;rsquo;s trademarks of &amp;ldquo;unassuming prose and truthful characterizations&amp;rdquo; are present. In King&amp;rsquo;s own words, he&amp;rsquo;ll go for terror, horror, and even the gross-out. Per Winter, Carrie &amp;ldquo;evokes the visceral, bringing the reader down to the guy level at which King operates best.</description></item><item><title>“Stephen King: The Art of Darkness” (Ch. 1-2)</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/29/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-ch-1-2/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/29/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-ch-1-2/</guid><description>The next book in my reading journal is &amp;ldquo;Stephen King: The Art of Darkness&amp;rdquo;, by Douglas E. Winter. Winter&amp;rsquo;s book is a critical look at King&amp;rsquo;s work up to the mid-80&amp;rsquo;s mixed with biographical information.
Chapter 1 - Introduction: Do the Dead Sing?
The first chapter and introduction to the work poses the question, &amp;ldquo;Do the Dead Sing?&amp;rdquo;. With that question, Winter brings us into the world of King by a broad overview of some of King&amp;rsquo;s works, and an analysis of how they fit into and have molded modern American Horror.</description></item><item><title>“From Shadowed Places”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/23/from-shadowed-places/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/23/from-shadowed-places/</guid><description>There are two aspects of this piece I find as valuable models for a writer. The first is the idea of death by inches. In my experience with horror, death come as a relatively swift blow - maybe there&amp;rsquo;s some torture, definitely some pain, but it is usually played out by a lot of tension and a quick end. Peter Lang has been under severe torture for months by the time we enter the story, and it shows through Matheson&amp;rsquo;s use of action, dialog, and description:</description></item><item><title>“Person to Person”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/22/person-to-person/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/22/person-to-person/</guid><description>Dialog like this is a challenge. Matheson&amp;rsquo;s main character, David Millman, is ultimately having a conversation with himself. He&amp;rsquo;s the crazy guy who hears voices in his head. I&amp;rsquo;ve written a couple of pieces that have this happen in them, but I haven&amp;rsquo;t been able to pull them off so well (in my humble opinion). Why is it that this story works but my own efforts haven&amp;rsquo;t?
I think it&amp;rsquo;s because when I&amp;rsquo;ve done it, my crazy main character sounds&amp;hellip; crazy.</description></item><item><title>“The Funeral”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/21/the-funeral/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/21/the-funeral/</guid><description>What I found most useful in this story is the sense of perspective, and how the POV character needn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily be the main character. The story is told from Morton Silkline&amp;rsquo;s perspective - the Director of a little cut-rate funeral home. While the story is his, I would argue that he doesn&amp;rsquo;t really experience any change and isn&amp;rsquo;t really the main character. It&amp;rsquo;s the vampire Ludwig Asper who is looking for a change, and ultimately receives it in the form of the funeral he never had.</description></item><item><title>“Mad House”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/18/mad-house/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/18/mad-house/</guid><description>Matheson uses a great focus technique to bring the reader into this story. The first four sections of &amp;ldquo;Mad House&amp;rdquo; are told in present tense, after which the story switches to the usual past tense. These first four sections, which cover only a few pages, are very special. They are tightly focused on the main character and his anger problem. They are very action oriented, walking the reader through several incidents of conflict between the main character and his surroundings.</description></item><item><title>“Dress of White Silk”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/15/dress-of-white-silk/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/15/dress-of-white-silk/</guid><description>Telling a story from a child&amp;rsquo;s point of view is a challenge. Telling it in a child&amp;rsquo;s language is a challenge as well. This piece was a little difficult for me to get engaged with because of Matheson&amp;rsquo;s lack of punctuation and the poor grammar (both intentional). This has the feel of an experimental piece.
I think that to be an effective writer at this sort of thing takes a lot of practice.</description></item><item><title>“Witch War”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/14/witch-war/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2009 00:02:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/14/witch-war/</guid><description>Why didn&amp;rsquo;t someone tell me there were so many vignette&amp;rsquo;s in &amp;ldquo;I Am Legend&amp;rdquo;?
Anyhow, this little snippet is almost poetry. It&amp;rsquo;s a great collection of images given in clear, if abrupt, language:
Sky clearing its throat with thunder, picking and dropping long lightening from immeasurable shoulders. Rain hushing the world, bowing the trees, pocking earth. Square building, low, with one wall plastic.
It&amp;rsquo;s what really stands out to me here.</description></item><item><title>“Prey”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/14/prey/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2009 00:01:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/14/prey/</guid><description>This vignette by Matheson gives an interesting parallel between a horrible little Zuni fetish doll, and the power of a parent over their child. As a reader, I enjoyed the chase and suspense of the woman being hunted by this little hunter. It&amp;rsquo;s a cool little encounter.
What I found most valuable as a writer, though, is the phone conversation between mother and daughter, as well as their family dynamic. Mother is manipulative and demanding, and is preying on her daughter&amp;rsquo;s emotions.</description></item><item><title>Undead Blog</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/11/undead-blog/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2009 00:04:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/11/undead-blog/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve revived my blog. It&amp;rsquo;s been dead for about a year. Poor blog.
I started a Master of Arts program in Writing Popular Fiction at Seton Hill University at the end of June. Kismet - the first day of my first writer&amp;rsquo;s residency was also my birthday.
Anyhow, part of the program involves reading (of course). And that requires a reading journal. Perfect use for a blog.
Welcome back, poor little neglected blog.</description></item><item><title>“The Near Departed”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/11/the-near-departed/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2009 00:03:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/11/the-near-departed/</guid><description>Another interesting little vignette by Matheson. To be honest, though, I didn&amp;rsquo;t find anything particularly interesting from a writer&amp;rsquo;s perspective. The dialog is plain, there&amp;rsquo;s little action, no real sense of tension, and the ending is standard &amp;ldquo;Twilight Zone&amp;rdquo; material.</description></item><item><title>“I Am Legend” (Ch. 17 – 21)</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/11/i-am-legend-ch-17-21/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2009 00:02:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/11/i-am-legend-ch-17-21/</guid><description>These are the final chapters. Matheson does a great job of continuing to create change in Neville. He&amp;rsquo;s encountered another human who is apparently immune as well, Ruth. He&amp;rsquo;s cold and distrustful at first, now having been in isolation for about 3 years.
He suddenly realized that he had become an ill-tempered and inveterate bachelor again. He no longer thought about his wife, his child, his past life. The present was enough.</description></item><item><title>“Buried Talents”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/11/buried-talents/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2009 00:01:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/11/buried-talents/</guid><description>This vignette by Richard Matheson presents an interesting technique for escalation. It&amp;rsquo;s brief story of an odd man who plays a game at the fair, the one where you chuck ping-pong balls into a fishbowl, and never misses.
The escalation is just that - the man never misses. It is, by nature of the scene, repetitive, but it&amp;rsquo;s the repetition of the man&amp;rsquo;s success that builds the story, bringing the reader along.</description></item><item><title>“I Am Legend” (Ch. 12 – 16)</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/09/i-am-legend-ch-12-16/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/09/i-am-legend-ch-12-16/</guid><description>Here we find Neville hitting another brick wall. He thinks he&amp;rsquo;s figured out what&amp;rsquo;s causing the vampires - a Bacilli (germ) - but he can&amp;rsquo;t attribute all the vampire behaviors to it. So, what does he do? Well, by this point we know Neville pretty well - a man who, although he&amp;rsquo;s survived some pretty extreme circumstances, falls back to the drink when things get too challenging.
Man, it&amp;rsquo;s time this guy get a new tune.</description></item><item><title>“I Am Legend” (Ch. 9 – 11)</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/07/i-am-legend-ch-9-11/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/07/i-am-legend-ch-9-11/</guid><description>So here we get more of Neville&amp;rsquo;s backstory, the death of his wife, his determination to bury her instead of burn her, and the horror of her return as a vampire. It&amp;rsquo;s interesting, but what really interested me more in these chapters is how Matheson shows us real change in Neville.
Neville has continued sobering himself up, tackling his situation like a real problem solver. He refers a few time to his father&amp;rsquo;s belief in the scientific method as inspiration.</description></item><item><title>“I Am Legend” (Ch. 4 – 8)</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/06/i-am-legend-ch-4-8/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/06/i-am-legend-ch-4-8/</guid><description>Matheson turns Neville&amp;rsquo;s character around in these chapters. At the end of chapter 4, Neville has forgotten to wind his watch and is stuck out after dark, not even sure what time it is. He survives the attacks, and spends the next couple of months rebuilding his home, getting to things he&amp;rsquo;d never done (like soundproofing the walls). He then sets about trying to figure out what he can about the virus or plague or whatever it is that&amp;rsquo;s caused all the people to turn.</description></item><item><title>“I Am Legend” (Ch. 1 – 3)</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/04/i-am-legend-chapt-1-3/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/04/i-am-legend-chapt-1-3/</guid><description>Matheson&amp;rsquo;s first three chapters do something I always find very difficult to pull off. He managed to develop a character in isolation, without having any benefit of dialog with another character. The description and narration combine well to bring out poor Robert Neville&amp;rsquo;s ordinary world.
I think Matheson also does a great job of building up the attackers through their actions (and the one who constantly taunts - &amp;ldquo;Come out, Neville!</description></item><item><title>“Dance of the Dead”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/03/dance-of-the-dead/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/03/dance-of-the-dead/</guid><description>Richard Matheson&amp;rsquo;s short story, &amp;ldquo;Dance of the Dead&amp;rdquo;, is a fine example of matching up pacing and action. The story opens with four college kids racing across the plains in a &amp;ldquo;Rotor-Motors Convertible, Model C, 1997&amp;rdquo;. The kids are engaged in drinking, drugs, and sex as they head to Saint Louis to catch a &amp;ldquo;loopy&amp;rdquo; show.
Needle quivering at 130, two 5-mph notches from the gauge&amp;rsquo;s end. A sudden dip! Their young frames jolted and the thrown-up laughter of three was windswept into night.</description></item><item><title>My First Paying Market!</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2008/07/08/my-first-paying-market/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2008/07/08/my-first-paying-market/</guid><description>I got up this morning, groggy as hell. Yeah, getting up at 4 am will do that to ya. But, it&amp;rsquo;s paying off! In my inbox was my first acceptance notice! My short story, Gray, is to be published in the January 2009 edition of Necrotic Tissue!
Sweeeeet&amp;hellip; I&amp;rsquo;m going back to bed.</description></item><item><title>Colors</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2007/08/24/colors/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2007/08/24/colors/</guid><description>you sense my hesitation. good. This is the color of DREAM we are children, unseeing we open our eye unlocking the verse and meter of the universe. This is the color of FORGET it is here look closer. this is the color This is the color of SAD baby girl, club-footed opens her eyes. pressed between hot sun and rough mountain welcomed to the world by no one. This is the color of GREED whatever is written here it is not enough.</description></item><item><title>Wednesday</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2007/08/14/wednesday/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2007/08/14/wednesday/</guid><description>I hum and beep at my master, but he does not listen. He pounds on my keys furiously, typing out insubstantial things, embedding himself in the abstract.
I creak and moan. I shout to him, &amp;ldquo;Go outside! Go play! It&amp;rsquo;s too nice to sit here all day!&amp;rdquo;
He doesn&amp;rsquo;t hear, just continues typing.
I shrug my shoulders.
I am Wednesday.</description></item><item><title>incense</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2007/05/21/incense/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 May 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2007/05/21/incense/</guid><description>fresh smoke squirms through our sacred window, pierces yesterday&amp;#39;s angel those words, salt your voice, awake my flesh, dried a raw monopoly of god</description></item><item><title>wet bug</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2007/05/12/wet-bug/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 May 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2007/05/12/wet-bug/</guid><description>squirming through the marbled world when you remember words remember the copper tang, the smoky perfume, the sad, warm woman your work must be porcelain steel rythms</description></item><item><title>translucent prisoner</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2007/05/09/translucent-prisoner/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 May 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2007/05/09/translucent-prisoner/</guid><description>their wild steel universe surrounds him broken through sex, velvet worry - once live - now devoured color perhaps, sister, you listen - stiff lipped laugh, trembling explore them, pick and haunt, time stream pooling Original Images [ Achi Tryptichon ]
[ AbuGraibAbuse11 ]
[ AbuGraibAbuse14 ]
[ ForgetMeNotFlower ]
[ A Galvanized Corpse ]</description></item><item><title>Chernobyl and Prypiat</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2007/04/05/chernobyl_prypiat/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Apr 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2007/04/05/chernobyl_prypiat/</guid><description>A great disaster. For a novel I started working on in October 2006, I started doing some research. There&amp;rsquo;s a portion of it that takes place in an old, abandoned city, one that had been left in destitution for centuries, so I was looking around for theories on what happens to a modern city when left to the forces of nature. To my shame, I had forgotten about the Chernobyl disaster.</description></item><item><title>End of NaNoWriMo</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/12/02/end-of-nanowrimo/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Dec 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/12/02/end-of-nanowrimo/</guid><description>NaNoWriMo wrapped up, of course, on November 30. How&amp;rsquo;d I do? I wound up with a word count of 48,459. Not the goal of NaNoWriMo, I know. But, it satisfies me that with an outline, and setting aside a few hours a night for writing 5 out of 7 days a week, I can make some tremendous progress towards a novel. Personally, after doing this the second time, I&amp;rsquo;ve come to agree with these wise words - I&amp;rsquo;d rather have spent the time writing something worth reading than cranking out 50,000 words worth of crap.</description></item><item><title>NaNoWriMo</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/11/01/nanowrimo/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/11/01/nanowrimo/</guid><description>Today kicks off NaNoWriMo. I&amp;rsquo;ve completed most of my novel&amp;rsquo;s outline, and I cranked out over 1500 words in just a few hours. The outline thing seems to have gotten me off to a great start! My writing came easily, I didn&amp;rsquo;t have to debate plot lines, or wonder where the hell I&amp;rsquo;m going with it - all I had to do now was write the scenes I&amp;rsquo;ve already laid out.</description></item><item><title>Preparing for NaNoWriMo</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/10/17/preparing-for-nanowrimo/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Oct 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/10/17/preparing-for-nanowrimo/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;m actually preparing myself for NaNoWriMo this year. I suppose it&amp;rsquo;s really just a coincidence, but I&amp;rsquo;m creating an outline for my novel, &amp;ldquo;The Secret of Kingship&amp;rdquo;. I finished reading Robert McKee&amp;rsquo;s book, &amp;ldquo;Story&amp;rdquo;, and it has inspired me. It truly gave me a better understanding of story telling in the modern age.
Anyhow, I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on an actual outline, character dossiers, and other such stuff for a week or so now.</description></item><item><title>The Sin of Self-Publishing</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/10/06/the-sin-of-self-publishing/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/10/06/the-sin-of-self-publishing/</guid><description>It seems to me that self-publishing has an awful reputation in the literary community. I think the view is that if you&amp;rsquo;re not good enough to get picked up by a major magazine or publishing house, then you&amp;rsquo;re just not worth reading.
However, we see more and more in other arts that self-publishing and promoting can break the industry barrier. And, in my opinion, the independently funded and promoted works in many ways exceed the quality of the mainstream channels.</description></item><item><title>Becoming</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/10/05/becoming/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/10/05/becoming/</guid><description>A young lawyer joins a new firm. Shortly after, he begins to undergo some bizarre physiological changes. He loses his appetite, is unable to drink much of anything, and has a host of flu-like symptoms.
Not long after this begins, he receives a package - no return address, no identifying marks. The post markings on it are in a foreign language and indecipherable. Inside he finds an unusual ring, pure silver, fashioned in the shape of a triangle with the relief image of folded hands inside of it.</description></item><item><title>Asylum Angels</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/08/20/asylum-angels/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/08/20/asylum-angels/</guid><description>Belief in the moon, where we end abated and objecting, cold distance setting inch upon historical inch. We hastily practice solitude, overcast angels in sheepskin jackets, limiting the rolling offenses unpaid to Sacred Support. We are fainting angels, angels, cold and distant, wrapping flies in bullets, the sung grave unconcerned. Cease wont, asylum angels. Awaken Atlas and flee cleverness.</description></item><item><title>Partial Meal</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/08/17/partial-meal/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/08/17/partial-meal/</guid><description>Flesh-eating hearts nurtured on line-soup nurse ivory anguish that is bidden thirsty for us. Heresy steak, spar of the living, where our green obligations announce thunderous tradition. Coal redresses discontent implication, shudders resistance, a dizzy unseen statement. Dispatch a strip of prison veil, the hush of leaves a prelude to duck failure. Lunch, that obstructed, devoted meal.</description></item><item><title>Sensenbrenner Park</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/08/14/sensenbrenner-park/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Aug 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/08/14/sensenbrenner-park/</guid><description>An old man, used up by his years of corporate loyalty. He has spent each evening leaving work late, stopping by a fountain, tossing a coin in. No wishes, no prayers, just a donation. Now, his retirement eve, the end of an uneventful day with the obligatory cake and cards, he stops at the fountain one last time. It is later than usual, nearly midnight, and he is alone by the fountain.</description></item><item><title>RV dust</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/08/11/rv-dust/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/08/11/rv-dust/</guid><description>Hide desperation contained from wanting illusionary knowing life from memory As manifested sounds with soft chamber non-existence behold, my own wanting of another mirror reality</description></item><item><title>wikshun</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/08/08/wikshun/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Aug 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/08/08/wikshun/</guid><description>I have an idea&amp;hellip;.
Wiki&amp;rsquo;s have become awfully big, and they&amp;rsquo;re great at semantically linking information together. However, they&amp;rsquo;re most suited towards documentation and fact gathering. I&amp;rsquo;ve seen one site - The Fiction Wikia - that tries to apply the wiki concept to story telling, but I think it has several shortcomings. The most notable is that it forces each and every author on the site to use the same license, the GNU Free Documentation License, which is great for information sharing, but is in my opinion not well suited to the fiction writer.</description></item><item><title>Mirror</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/07/24/mirror/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Jul 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/07/24/mirror/</guid><description>Sublime ripples shadow purgatory wanting. This time mirrors my silence. Wanting and consumed, Sanguine waters rushing, My spirit wades to be freed. A frozen end.</description></item><item><title>Unforgotten</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/08/07/unforgotten/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Jul 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/08/07/unforgotten/</guid><description>Time conducting desperatio running sorrow of knowing illusory meaning traversing orchestral mirrors touch destiny contained within a self made mirror of defiance behold a lending of meaning</description></item><item><title>Distraction</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/07/13/distraction/</link><pubDate>Thu, 13 Jul 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/07/13/distraction/</guid><description>The world surrounds us with distractions. Television is a particularly sinister form, and I&amp;rsquo;m only lately coming to realize its actual power over people. Try sitting in a room with a television on and doing something else - something like read a book or (as I&amp;rsquo;ve often tried) writing.
It doesn&amp;rsquo;t work. We are drawn to it - it stimulates us more than most other readily accessible forms of entertainment. What happens to a person when he slowly comes to realize how much he truly has been distracted by television?</description></item><item><title>Institutionalized</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/25/institutionalized/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/25/institutionalized/</guid><description>I watched The Shawshank Redemption tonight. Not the first time I&amp;rsquo;ve seen it - and I had read the short story before the movie came out. Both are fine works. In the movie, Morgan Freeman&amp;rsquo;s character, &amp;lsquo;Red&amp;rsquo;, gives this little speech about how one of the other characters has been in so long, he&amp;rsquo;s become institutionalized. In essence, it&amp;rsquo;s what happens to a person who has been in prison so long, they stop knowing how to be valuable outside the prison setting.</description></item><item><title>Ghosts are crazy</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/22/ghosts-are-crazy/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/22/ghosts-are-crazy/</guid><description>I can&amp;rsquo;t remember where I heard this, but recently, I heard something that may seem obvious to most, but had totally escaped me. The reason we&amp;rsquo;re afraid of ghosts is that they&amp;rsquo;re lost souls, they&amp;rsquo;re all crazy because they&amp;rsquo;re trapped here - someplace they shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be. And we instinctively know that - that since they are trapped, caught and bound to a place that is in opposition of what they have become, they are driven insane.</description></item><item><title>Abbey of Delusion</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/21/abbey-of-delusion/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/21/abbey-of-delusion/</guid><description>I built my self an Abbey of delusion content with angles, sharp and thick; a discharge of underground ink. I came upon a downcast flood of commercial recipes, dawning thanks to the fool who juggles an excess meal. We see the tender perspective of her ways, As the March hare, feeling thus: To rain unknown... To murder the threshold bricks... To subjective patient breaks of thick deep... To label (in murmurs) the deep.</description></item><item><title>Cabbie</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/20/cabbie/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/20/cabbie/</guid><description>After having the worst day of his life, an unscrupulous New Yorker has a difficult time making his way home. He is repeatedly lost and abused, and is haunted throughout the night by a single, reappearing cabby that frightens him.</description></item><item><title>Tension</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/14/tension/</link><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/14/tension/</guid><description>Apollo&amp;#39;s fissured time, muted and screened by circumstance. This silky night of tears eclipses the eye in shuttered laughter. Delicious tragedy, life&amp;#39;s movement a conflict of fractured author and masqued audience.</description></item><item><title>Magic Baby</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/12/magic-baby/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/12/magic-baby/</guid><description>This one is actually my wife&amp;rsquo;s idea.
This couple has this baby. The baby is very in tune to his/her parents, and it can pick up on what they wish for. It begins granting their wishes. Sounds a little weird, but I remember reading once that one of the Native American tribes believes (or believed) that we are born with knowledge of the language of the gods, and that we forget it as we grow up, forgetting completely by age 4.</description></item><item><title>station</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/11/station/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/11/station/</guid><description>inhaling a starless breath we limp under a hanging world whose pressured shadow tastes hot like silky desire existence kissed by imaging</description></item><item><title>Chaplain of Fabulous Paper</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/10/chaplain-of-fabulous-paper/</link><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/10/chaplain-of-fabulous-paper/</guid><description>Put out the eyes of foresight, which underneath taught torrential calm despite the thrilling clear acumen. Take ease in the transparent steady slumber which it allies like privileged unmasked liquid, binding sanity to impulse, a manifold chord. Demonic rum, harmless to the churchman&amp;#39;s skeleton, that rabbit of relief and sovereign egotist, loops prejudice and indexes possibilities preying on resident thoughts which tingle with ill passing. Enter the transfusion of flashing standstills germane to grasping, leaving us to stare at appealing refractions.</description></item><item><title>The Cat Ladies</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/09/the-cat-ladies/</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/09/the-cat-ladies/</guid><description>An animal rescue group is clearing out a house where a woman and her elderly mother live in extremely unhealthy conditions, along with about 100 cats. What they find deep beneath the 50 years worth of accumulated junk and mounds of cat excrement is much more than any of them expected.</description></item><item><title>Stalks of Faith</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/08/stalks-of-faith/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/08/stalks-of-faith/</guid><description>A helpless yellow disciple of anger, precariously fluttering against the concrete earth. Preachers and brethren, hung by the umbilical stalk of faith, shake and chortle. The wavering spine of desire, snapped and severed by the coarse sparks of flesh. Red tenderness is found by flames of will.</description></item><item><title>1000 Words</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/07/1000-words/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/07/1000-words/</guid><description>1000 words per day. If you write 1000 words per day, you can crank out a lot of writing. I&amp;rsquo;ve seen indications around that a writer&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;apprenticeship&amp;rsquo; should amount to one million written words. If you can do 1000 words a day, then an apprenticeship amounts to about 3 years.
I have no idea if that stuff about an &amp;lsquo;apprenticeship&amp;rsquo; is true, if it really takes one million words before a writer achieves that almost mindless level of production to consider themselves a writer.</description></item><item><title>Story Lines – Introduction</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/06/story-lines-introduction/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/06/story-lines-introduction/</guid><description>Every story stems from a crisis. As readers, we are most interested in the struggles of our fellow humans. Our interest is most easily captured by bad news, stress, conflict. Not that the outcomes must be bad &amp;ndash; on the contrary, we love stories that depict triumph in the face of adversity. But the thing that most easily grabs us is when tension, crisis, and turmoil erupt into everyday life.</description></item><item><title>Abandon</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/05/abandon/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/05/abandon/</guid><description>Mildly blamed abandon, a vanishing madness poignant over the boundlessness of hot yard, pagan-hearted discontent; of sweet man, with verbatim extreme control. Mighty punishment out of turn casting the bound shrine, a bygone tomb, where indeed electricity arcs truly their legend. Regional bloody faith itemizes the witnesses. Grave-wide perceptible excuses condemn religious humility with calculated infected ejaculations. Weakness wrought out of structure holding dearly to the offending horn. Faltering skins swallow anything, downcast moonlight their restraint.</description></item><item><title>Start of a new day</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/04/start-of-a-new-day/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/04/start-of-a-new-day/</guid><description>I set up this new site today. It&amp;rsquo;s my first step in publicizing myself as a writer. My wife recently gave birth to our first son (also David L. Day), and during the course of her pregnancy, as well as the three weeks I was off after the delivery, I came to realize something. I want my son to learn a lot of things about life, and one in particular is that he should never give up on pursing his dreams.</description></item><item><title>“Stephen King&amp;#58; The Art of Darkness” – The Haunted House</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/28/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-the-haunted-house/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/28/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-the-haunted-house/</guid><description>Another element Winter discusses in his analysis of King is the haunted house. What strikes me as most interesting with this is that, while I think Winter does a good job of identifying the various &amp;lsquo;haunted houses&amp;rsquo; in King&amp;rsquo;s works, he never seems to talk about what the idea of &amp;lsquo;setting as character&amp;rsquo; directly.
For context, Winter identifies the following as noteworthy &amp;lsquo;haunted houses&amp;rsquo;:
The Martsen House in &amp;lsquo;Salem&amp;rsquo;s Lot The Overlook Hotel in The Shining The Agincourt Hotel in The Talisman The Dark Tower in The Dark Tower series * The last one is my own addition.</description></item></channel></rss>