<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Broken_abbey on David L. Day</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/categories/broken_abbey/</link><description>Recent content in Broken_abbey on David L. Day</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.davidlday.com/categories/broken_abbey/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Goodbye WordPress</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/03/04/goodbye-wordpress/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/03/04/goodbye-wordpress/</guid><description>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m done with WordPress. It&amp;rsquo;s wonderful, but it&amp;rsquo;s too much for me. I know in
this day and age it seems every aspiring writer runs a tight blog, with frequent
posts and guests and insightful advice on writing. But that&amp;rsquo;s not for me.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I spent too much time over the past few years tweaking and tuning WordPress, not
enough time actually writing posts, and beating myself up over both. So I&amp;rsquo;m
ditching the pretense that I&amp;rsquo;m a blogger. I&amp;rsquo;m not. I want to write wonderful
short stories and novels, and while blogging may help some in their pursuit of
genre writing, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t help me. It stresses me out, which is not what I need.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Time for a Change</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2011/07/06/time-for-a-change/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2011/07/06/time-for-a-change/</guid><description>&lt;p>For the past two years, I used this blog to publish most of my reading journals
for my graduate program. I graduated in June, and now it&amp;rsquo;s time to give this
place a new purpose.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve put a lot of thought into what kind of thing this site should morph into,
and I haven&amp;rsquo;t quite decided yet. I think I&amp;rsquo;ll start doing book reviews, but
we&amp;rsquo;ll see. For now, I&amp;rsquo;ll post the occasional thought and progress as I work
toward publication.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Scrivener for Windows… and Linux?</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/11/25/scrivener-for-windows-and-linux/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/11/25/scrivener-for-windows-and-linux/</guid><description>&lt;p>There are some interesting things going on at
&lt;a href="http://www.literatureandlatte.com/">Literature &amp;amp; Latte&lt;/a>. First, they&amp;rsquo;ve
released a Windows Beta version of their unique and popular writing software
&lt;a href="http://www.literatureandlatte.com/scrivener.php">Scrivener&lt;/a>, which isn&amp;rsquo;t really
news. However, what doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem well-known yet is that on their message boards,
a group of folks is playing with an unofficial version for Linux.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you&amp;rsquo;re really interested in using Scrivener, I urge you to sign up for the
&lt;a href="http://www.literatureandlatte.com/scrivenerforwindows/">Windows Beta&lt;/a> and try
it out.
&lt;a href="http://lifehacker.com/comment/31418541/">Use Wine if you&amp;rsquo;re Linux only&lt;/a>. Also,
see the
&lt;a href="http://www.literatureandlatte.com/forum/viewforum.php?f=30">Linux user thread&lt;/a>
on L&amp;amp;L&amp;rsquo;s forum. Sign up; help out. Finally, be aware that I do not give any
files directly in this post. I only link to files on L&amp;amp;L&amp;rsquo;s forums.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Thoughts on The Exorcist by William Peter Blatty</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/10/17/thoughts-on-the-exorcist-by-william-peter-blatty/</link><pubDate>Sun, 17 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/10/17/thoughts-on-the-exorcist-by-william-peter-blatty/</guid><description>&lt;p>Most people should be familiar with Blatty&amp;rsquo;s
&lt;a href="http://amzn.to/b3hfZd">&lt;em>The Exorcist&lt;/em>&lt;/a> by now. I mean, it&amp;rsquo;s a classic, right?
The mere mention of the title suggests Linda Blair spewing ungodly amounts of
pea soup. So no introduction is necessary. It is definitely a great horror novel
that everyone with even a minor interest in horror should read. Go read it. Now.
I mean it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Okay, all due praise aside, there are two things about the novel that stood out
for me as a writer.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Thoughts on Ansen Dibell’s “Plot”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/09/28/thoughts-on-ansen-dibells-plot/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/09/28/thoughts-on-ansen-dibells-plot/</guid><description>&lt;p>One of the most challenging things I struggle with as both a writer of fiction
and a student of literature (yeah, they always go together) is which tool to use
when. I believe that while reading and writing are intricately related&amp;ndash;you must
be well-read to be well-written&amp;ndash;they don&amp;rsquo;t use the same mental tools.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The term plot (my archenemy when it comes to writing) appears in both toolkits,
and I think that is terribly confusing.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Thoughts on Nate Kenyon’s “Sparrow Rock”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/08/24/thoughts-on-nate-kenyons-sparrow-rock/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/08/24/thoughts-on-nate-kenyons-sparrow-rock/</guid><description>&lt;p>I just finished reading &lt;a href="http://www.natekenyon.com">Nate Kenyon&lt;/a>&amp;rsquo;s latest novel,
&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Sparrow-Rock-Nate-Kenyon/dp/0843963778/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;s=books&amp;amp;qid=1270214210&amp;amp;sr=1-1">&lt;em>Sparrow Rock&lt;/em>&lt;/a>,
a story of a group of high school kids who find themselves trapped in a bomb
shelter by accident just as the end of the world arrives. Read the official
synopsis from &lt;a href="http://natekenyon.com/sparrow-rock-synopsis">Nate&amp;rsquo;s site&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The novel has received excellent reviews at multiple sites, and I think the
praise is well-deserved. Kenyon has produced a fast-paced, engaging tale of
survival. This is the second book I&amp;rsquo;ve read by Kenyon. I read
&lt;em>&lt;a href="http://natekenyon.com/fiction/bloodstone-synopsis/2005/11/22">Bloodstone&lt;/a>&lt;/em>
some months back as a sample of a first novel, but have yet to get to a post on
it. I thought it an excellent tale as well, and I will keep his work at the top
of my list from here on out.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Thoughts on Bently Little’s “The Town”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/08/08/thoughts-on-bently-littles-the-town/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/08/08/thoughts-on-bently-littles-the-town/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="http://bit.ly/ayRVNF">Bently Little&lt;/a>&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="http://amzn.to/a5BpnT">&lt;em>The Town&lt;/em>&lt;/a> was
published in 2000, and I think even 10 years later it holds up as a good story.
I found Bently&amp;rsquo;s take on small-town horror refreshing in many ways, even though
the idea of horror in a small town isn&amp;rsquo;t so unique by today&amp;rsquo;s standards. The
story involves a family of six who move back to the father&amp;rsquo;s home town after
winning the lottery to simplify their lives and exchange the dangers of LA for
the assumed tranquility of McGuane, Arizona.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Why Character Matters</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/07/05/why-character-matters/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/07/05/why-character-matters/</guid><description>&lt;p>I just finished reading &lt;a href="http://www.edwardleeonline.com/">Edward Lee&lt;/a>&amp;rsquo;s
&lt;a href="http://amzn.to/cjs1rX">&lt;em>The Golem&lt;/em>&lt;/a>. This is my first encounter with any of
Edward Lee&amp;rsquo;s work. I believe every author should have two chances, so Ed Lee has
one left. To me, the book read like a first draft, but I&amp;rsquo;ll get to that.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We don&amp;rsquo;t see the golem used much in popular fiction. I can only recall one
instance where I&amp;rsquo;ve seen it used&amp;ndash;an old episode of the X-Files called
&lt;a href="http://bit.ly/campOV">&lt;em>Kaddish&lt;/em>&lt;/a>. Lee brings the reader a modern version of an
old Jewish folk tale based on &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/bArhVJ">Judah Loew&lt;/a>, a 16th century
rabbi who created a golem to defend a Prague ghetto from anti-Semitic attacks.
Lee brings the folktale to life with vibrant rituals and an exploration of a
dark sect of Kabbalah based on Kischuph. The story revolves around the small
town of Lowensport, Maryland. In 1880, a group of Jewish refugees from Prague,
led by the evil rabbi Gavriel Loew, construct two golems to defend themselves
from the attack of the Conner clan, a local group of settlers lead by an
ex-military deserter. The story is told in parallel with the present-day tale of
Seth Kohn and his girlfriend Judy, who move into the old Lowen mansion and find
themselves in the middle of a plan by Gavriel&amp;rsquo;s great-great-great grandson to
resurrect Gavriel as a golem and&amp;ndash;you guessed it&amp;ndash;take over the world, or at
least small part of it.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Manuscript Templates</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/06/09/manuscript-templates/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/06/09/manuscript-templates/</guid><description>&lt;p>Part of being a professional writer is ensuring your submissions meet format
guidelines. &lt;a href="http://www.shunn.net/format/">William Shunn&lt;/a> developed a set of
format guidelines, originally published in December 1998 edition of
&lt;a href="http://www.writerswrite.com/journal/dec98/shunn.htm">Writers Write: The Internet Writing Journal&lt;/a>.
He also provides a set of &lt;a href="http://www.shunn.net/format/wp.html">templates&lt;/a> on
his site, but unfortunately they are only for WordPerfect. I use
&lt;a href="http://www.openoffice.org">OpenOffice&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I decided to create my own templates based on his guidelines and offer them here
for all to use. I emailed Mr. Shunn several times over the past year to ask
permission to post these, and never received a response. I decided to go ahead
and offer them anyhow, and if Mr. Shunn objects, I will remove them.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>One Helluva Ghost Story</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/04/27/one-helluva-ghost-story/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/04/27/one-helluva-ghost-story/</guid><description>&lt;p>I just finished reading Tom Piccirilli&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>A Choir of Ill Children&lt;/em>&amp;ndash;for the
second time. I read it back in February and decided that to do it any justice, I
needed to set it aside and reread it. It&amp;rsquo;s not an overly complex book, but I&amp;rsquo;m
not used to the Southern style. The last book I read that felt stylistically
similar was Faulkner&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>As I Lay Dying&lt;/em>&amp;ndash;over fifteen years ago.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The first thing that I noticed is the uniqueness of every character. I was
familiar with the book prior to reading it, and had an admittedly biased
expectation that at least some of the characters would be backwater rednecks.
Piccirilli, however, invests each character with a distinct personality that I
don&amp;rsquo;t believe fit any stereotypes. Further, I expected at least some of the
dialog to have poor diction. Again, I was totally wrong. Most of the dialog uses
good diction&amp;ndash;Piccirilli makes very prudent use of &amp;ldquo;ain&amp;rsquo;t&amp;quot;s throughout, for
which I&amp;rsquo;m grateful.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Another Round of How-To, Part 3</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/04/07/another-round-of-how-to-part-3/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/04/07/another-round-of-how-to-part-3/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is the last of a three-part journal on &lt;em>How to Write Tales of Horror,
Fantasy &amp;amp; Science Fiction&lt;/em>, Edited by J. N. Williamson, a collection of How-To
articles by some of the best horror writers, circa 1987.
&lt;a href="../2010/03/01/another-round-of-how-to/index.html">Part one&lt;/a> covered chapters
1-8; &lt;a href="https://www.davidlday.com/2010/03/23/another-round-of-how-to-part-2/">part two&lt;/a> covered chapters
9-18.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The advice found in these final chapters still mirrors advice found in the
wonderful &lt;a href="http://www.horror.org/hwabooks.htm#write_horr">&lt;em>On Writing Horror&lt;/em>&lt;/a>,
another collection of How-To articles by some of horror&amp;rsquo;s best writers
circa 2007. But here&amp;rsquo;s one thing I&amp;rsquo;ve learned from reading both books (and a
slew of other How-To books) that&amp;rsquo;s not actually in either. I&amp;rsquo;m sick of reading
How-To books on writing. In my genre session during last writer&amp;rsquo;s residency,
&lt;a href="http://gorelets.com/">Dr. Arnzen&lt;/a> commented that if all you read are how-to
books, then all you&amp;rsquo;ll be able to write are how-to books. I&amp;rsquo;ve grown to
appreciate his statement. With that, let me get through this and hopefully I&amp;rsquo;ll
be done with anything How-To for a while.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Another Round of How-To, Part 2</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/03/23/another-round-of-how-to-part-2/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/03/23/another-round-of-how-to-part-2/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is part two of a three-part journal on &lt;em>How to Write Tales of Horror,
Fantasy &amp;amp; Science Fiction&lt;/em>, Edited by J. N. Williamson, a collection of How-To
articles by some of the best horror writers, circa 1987.
&lt;a href="https://www.davidlday.com/2010/03/01/another-round-of-how-to/">Part one&lt;/a> covered chapters 1-8.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In my first post, I mentioned how strikingly similar the advice is to that found
in &lt;em>On Writing Horror&lt;/em>, another collection of How-To articles by some of
horror&amp;rsquo;s best writers circa 2007. I&amp;rsquo;ve still found this to hold true. I don&amp;rsquo;t
mean that as a slight against either work, as the essays in both are unique to
the authors. For me, this reinforces that the advice found within each work has
a certain timeless quality to it even though markets have changed.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Another Round of How-To</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/03/01/another-round-of-how-to/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/03/01/another-round-of-how-to/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is the first of three posts on &lt;em>How to Write Tales of Horror, Fantasy &amp;amp;
Science Fiction&lt;/em>, Edited by J. N. Williamson. The book is a collection of How-To
articles by some of the best horror writers, circa 1987.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Late last year I did a series of posts on &lt;em>On Writing Horror&lt;/em>, another
collection of How-To articles by some of horror&amp;rsquo;s best writers circa 2007.
Twenty years separate the publication of these two books, but so far I haven&amp;rsquo;t
found anything other than the market survey that really differentiate the two.
I&amp;rsquo;ve commented before that information repeated across authors is usually good
advice, and I think that&amp;rsquo;s still true. But, I&amp;rsquo;m a little disappointed that I
haven&amp;rsquo;t found anything new here. Yet.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Measuring Quality – Words or Pages</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/01/31/measuring-quality-words-or-pages/</link><pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/01/31/measuring-quality-words-or-pages/</guid><description>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m a couple of weeks into my second term in
&lt;a href="http://http://www.setonhill.edu/academics/fiction/index.cfm">Seton Hill&amp;rsquo;s MA WPF&lt;/a>
program. My thesis is a marketable horror novel, targeted at 350 pages. My
personal goal is to complete the 1st draft by the end of this term, and spend
the rest of my program editing and revision. Or rewriting if my mentors so
command.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>None of that is particularly interesting, but they&amp;rsquo;re facts that lay the
groundwork for what&amp;rsquo;s been on my mind lately. Every professional writer develops
their own flavor of discipline, without which they would be unable to sustain
professional standing. It&amp;rsquo;s actually pretty common among most successful people
regardless of profession to develop a habit around their chosen work. What I&amp;rsquo;ve
been interested in is how writers measure their progress?&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Back to work...</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/01/08/back-to-work/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/01/08/back-to-work/</guid><description>&lt;p>Just got back from residency orientation @ Seton Hill. It&amp;rsquo;s nice to be back,
even if it meant driving 4 hours through snow. I had a great break, had a couple
of good reads while I was off. First was John Scalzi&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>Old Man&amp;rsquo;s War&lt;/em>, a very
entertaining science fiction book. It&amp;rsquo;s not my typical flavor, but it kept me
reading, full of good action and interesting characters.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My other read was &lt;em>The Mammoth Book of Best New Horror, Volume 20&lt;/em>, edited by
Stephen Jones. It&amp;rsquo;s filled with some excellent short horror from 2008, and
definitely worth the time. It&amp;rsquo;s late, I&amp;rsquo;m tired, so I won&amp;rsquo;t do any sort of
review of them, but here&amp;rsquo;s a list of the one&amp;rsquo;s that appealed most to me:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A Bit of a Break</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/12/01/a-bit-of-a-break/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/12/01/a-bit-of-a-break/</guid><description>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve been on break from school since beginning of November, so I took the
opportunity to brush up on mechanics. Specifically, I took a much-needed browse
through the old &lt;em>Elements of Style&lt;/em>. Good little book. But, I wanted more. So, I
found a more contemporary take on style, &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/633eMV">Sin and Syntax&lt;/a>,
by Constance Hale. It&amp;rsquo;s longer than Elements. There&amp;rsquo;s plenty of praise for the
book out in the wild; I&amp;rsquo;ll say I&amp;rsquo;m glad I took the time to read it as well. How
do I know? Some of my writing from as recent as a year ago makes me cringe.
[sigh] Shortly after I finished, I set about some serious revision work on a few
older short stories.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Down to Business</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/21/down-to-business/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/21/down-to-business/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the end, writing is like any other endeavor. Sure, there is a significant and
compelling creative aspect to it, almost mystical at times. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t just
happen, though. The magic comes through sweat and rigor. King lays this out in
his final section of &lt;em>On Writing&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>His opinion is that there are 4 classes of writer: Bad, Competent, Good, and
Genius. He states that there are 2 theses to his book:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Tools of the Trade</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/18/tools-of-the-trade/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/18/tools-of-the-trade/</guid><description>&lt;p>In part two of On Writing, King gives an overview of what he considers the
essential tools for every writer&amp;rsquo;s toolbox. The analogy is interesting, and the
story he provides at the start demonstrates an excellent point: Always have all
your tools with you so you can tackle any unexpected situation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So what goes in this metaphorical toolbox?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The first layer consists of common tools. The most common tool, per King, is
vocabulary. It&amp;rsquo;s something we all have to varying degrees. I really appreciate
King&amp;rsquo;s take on vocabulary, which is essentially, learn to use what you have and
don&amp;rsquo;t worry about developing more. Your vocabulary develops as a by-product of
reading. All writers are readers first, right?&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A Fogged-Out Landscape</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/17/a-fogged-out-landscape/</link><pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/17/a-fogged-out-landscape/</guid><description>&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s wonderful how much we can learn from stories, particularly when well told.
Stephen King spends the first part of his book, &lt;em>On Writing&lt;/em>, by walking the
reader through a series of &amp;lsquo;fogged-out&amp;rsquo; memories. The book itself is about
writing. But he sets the stage by doing what he does best, and tells the story
of what made him what he is today.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I can&amp;rsquo;t say if it was intentional on his part, but in telling what he considers
his &amp;ldquo;C.V.&amp;rdquo;, King demonstrates a series of important lessons that were critical
in shaping him. Notice I said demonstrate. I think this is, perhaps, one of the
first aspects he teaches us. His book is about writing, but instead of listing
out a series of lessons, he shows us what he learned and how he learned it. It
is a vehement adherence to the old adage of &amp;ldquo;show, don&amp;rsquo;t tell&amp;rdquo;. I&amp;rsquo;ve read too
many books and articles on writing that do little more than list out rules or
guidelines or maxims or adages or aphorisms or whatever word you want to use.
But, in the end, they&amp;rsquo;re nothing more than a handful of words on a page that
leave the reader with little more than a sense that there&amp;rsquo;s something to
memorize. There&amp;rsquo;s no feeling in the lessons they impart, no connection to the
reader. Just rules.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“On Writing… oh, to hell with it.</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/15/on-writing-oh-to-hell-with-it/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2009 02:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/15/on-writing-oh-to-hell-with-it/</guid><description>&lt;p>The last section of &amp;ldquo;On Writing Horror&amp;rdquo; is all about the business aspect of
being a writer. It provides a nice overview of the current markets, good
resources for research and promotion, and some worthwhile advice from editors
and writers alike.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here&amp;rsquo;s the advice I&amp;rsquo;m taking right now, given by &lt;em>Night Shade Books&lt;/em>:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Write what you think is your best book. Put it in a trunk and write another
one. Do this four times. Then start sending your novels out for submission.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“On Writing Horror” – Part Seven</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/15/on-writing-horror-part-7/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2009 00:01:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/15/on-writing-horror-part-7/</guid><description>&lt;p>Part 7 of &lt;em>On Writing Horror&lt;/em> is titled &amp;ldquo;Genre and Subgenre&amp;rdquo;, but the 10
articles also cover concerns with medium as well (screenplay, theater, audio).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Archetypes and Fearful Allure: Writing Erotic Horror, &lt;em>Nancy Kilpatrick&lt;/em>&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I really struggled with this one. Kilpatrick seems to rely heavily on the
concept of Archetypes, and the crux of her advice can be summed up in the
following quote:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>This means that the energy embedded in the image resonates with all readers
because it taps into and stirs up the collective unconscious.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“On Writing Horror” – Part Six</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/11/on-writing-horror-part-six/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/11/on-writing-horror-part-six/</guid><description>&lt;p>Part 6 of &lt;em>On Writing Horror&lt;/em> is titled &amp;ldquo;Tradition and Modern Times&amp;rdquo;, a series
of articles covering horror tradition and its place in our modern literature.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>No More Silver Mirrors: The Monster in Our Times, &lt;em>Karen E. Taylor&lt;/em>&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Taylor addresses how the old monsters can be made new again. She&amp;rsquo;s got some good
advice, and I&amp;rsquo;ll get to that in a second, but there&amp;rsquo;s something she says early
on that is direct opposition to what at least one other author claims in this
series of articles. Taylor states:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“On Writing Horror” – Part Five</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/09/on-writing-horror-part-five/</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/09/on-writing-horror-part-five/</guid><description>&lt;p>Part 5 of &lt;em>On Writing Horror&lt;/em> is titled &amp;ldquo;Horror, Art, Innovation, Excellence&amp;rdquo;.
Five articles. Actually, 4 articles and one interesting interview with Harlan
Ellison.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Innovation in Horror, &lt;em>Jeanne Cavelos&lt;/em>&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m starting to see patterns of advice in these articles, even though they have
different emphasis. Cavelos talks in terms of innovation, but starts with the
foundational advice of read a lot, read both in and out of the genre. Doing so
helps the amateur writer avoid writing something that&amp;rsquo;s old under the false
belief that they&amp;rsquo;ve written something new. Fair enough, know what&amp;rsquo;s been done
before so you can truly come up with something knew.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“On Writing Horror” – Part Four</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/07/on-writing-horror-part-four/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/07/on-writing-horror-part-four/</guid><description>&lt;p>Part 4 of &lt;em>On Writing Horror&lt;/em> is titled &amp;ldquo;Horror Crafting&amp;rdquo;, and encompasses 7
articles on the craft. So many articles, and much of it is advice I&amp;rsquo;ve heard
before, so I&amp;rsquo;m going to keep this as short as I can.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>&lt;em>Such Horrible People&lt;/em>, Tina Jens&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Per Jens, &amp;ldquo;Horror is about how people react &lt;em>when they encounter&lt;/em> the plot.&amp;rdquo; So
to have good horror, we need good characters who interact with the plot. That&amp;rsquo;s
nothing new to me, and it&amp;rsquo;s sound advice.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“On Writing Horror” – Part Three</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/04/on-writing-horror-part-three/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/04/on-writing-horror-part-three/</guid><description>&lt;p>Part 3 of &lt;em>On Writing Horror&lt;/em> is titled &amp;ldquo;Developing Horror Concepts&amp;rdquo;. It
contains four articles dealing with conceiving and developing ideas for horror.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>&lt;em>A World of Dark and Disturbing Ideas&lt;/em>, J. N. Williamson&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Williamson chooses to speak in terms of &amp;ldquo;useful premise&amp;rdquo; as opposed to &amp;ldquo;idea&amp;rdquo;,
and I can appreciate his working definition. Idea&amp;rsquo;s are great, but they are
largely useless if they cannot or will not be executed. This is true pretty much
regardless of profession or circumstance. Per Williamson, a &amp;ldquo;useful premise&amp;rdquo; is:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“On Writing Horror” – Part Two</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/03/on-writing-horror-part-two/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/03/on-writing-horror-part-two/</guid><description>&lt;p>Part 2 of &lt;em>On Writing Horror&lt;/em>, titled &amp;ldquo;An Education in Horror&amp;rdquo;, briefly
addresses a horror writer&amp;rsquo;s education in four articles.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>&lt;em>What You Are Meant to Know: Twenty-One Horror Classics&lt;/em>, Robert Weinberg&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Weinberg&amp;rsquo;s message is pretty clear - know your genre. He suggests that, in order
to be marketable, you must be original. And, in order to be original, you must
know what&amp;rsquo;s already been done. Aside from the mechanics of writing, a horror
writer must be familiar with what&amp;rsquo;s been done. I think that&amp;rsquo;s great advice
regardless of genre, that in order to be creative - combine the usual in unusual
ways - you must first know what is usual. He lists out 21 books that every
horror writer should read. Sad to say, I&amp;rsquo;ve only read 6 and seen the movie
version of 4. I guess I have some reading to do&amp;hellip;&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“On Writing Horror” – Part One</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/01/on-writing-horror-part-one/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/01/on-writing-horror-part-one/</guid><description>&lt;p>Today I&amp;rsquo;m starting my journal entries for &lt;em>On Writing Horror&lt;/em>, A Handbook by
&lt;a href="http://www.horror.org">The Horror Writer&amp;rsquo;s Association&lt;/a>. The book contains
about 50 individual articles, divided among 8 different sections, so I&amp;rsquo;m going
to match my entries up to the sections rather than address the articles
individually.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Part one is called &amp;ldquo;Horror, Literature, and Horror Literature&amp;rdquo;. The three
articles in this section seem to address whether Horror Fiction is or isn&amp;rsquo;t
Literary Fiction. Or more broadly, the contention between Genre Fiction and
Literary Fiction that seems to be pervasive, and has been for quite some time,
in the literary community.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“Urban Gothic” – No Signal</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/29/urban-gothic-no-signal/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/29/urban-gothic-no-signal/</guid><description>&lt;p>Screenwriter John August has an interesting little post on
&lt;a href="http://johnaugust.com/archives/2009/no-signal">cell phones&lt;/a> in the movies. It
includes a great little montage of movie clips showing phones not working,
getting smashed, etc. Why on earth do I care?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Brian Keene has this very problem in &lt;em>Urban Gothic&lt;/em>. In an era where it seems
everyone has a cell phone, how does a writer deal with it?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>By my count, there are six teenagers in Keene&amp;rsquo;s book, each of whom has their own
cell phone. They get trapped in an abandoned
(&lt;a href="https://www.davidlday.com/2009/09/28/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-the-haunted-house/">haunted&lt;/a>?)
house that&amp;rsquo;s in a bad neighborhood, but it&amp;rsquo;s a suburb of Camden, New Jersey. Not
exactly in the middle of nowhere. It&amp;rsquo;s actually well covered by AT&amp;amp;T, Verizon,
and Sprint. Yes, I checked, but not as any sort of petty criticism of Keene.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“Urban Gothic” and The Minotaur</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/24/urban-gothic-and-the-minotaur/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2009 00:02:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/24/urban-gothic-and-the-minotaur/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="http://www.briankeene.com/">Brian Keene’s&lt;/a> recently released &lt;em>Urban Gothic&lt;/em>
brought to mind the myth of the Minotaur. A group of teens is thrown into a
labyrinthine house whose twists and turns extend far below the ground in a
neglected neighborhood. Their first encounter is with a hulking, deformed
creature whose strength seems insurmountable.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Keene tells this story from multiple points of view, and I think that worked
really well for the fast-paced action. I noticed, too, that Keene give the
reader an immediate indication of POV change by having the POV character
identified, in most cases, in the first sentence of any section change. I
noticed it because I was looking for it, but I don’t think it was in any way
repetitive or distracting.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“Stephen King&amp;#58; The Art of Darkness” - Night Journey</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/24/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-night-journey/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2009 00:01:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/24/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-night-journey/</guid><description>&lt;p>What is the “night journey” in the context of Stephen King?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>First, Winter shows how all of King’s works deal with some sort of journey. The
idea of story as a journey is not new. Joseph Campbell is well known for his
“Hero’s Journey”, and I’ve often encountered the aphorism that “the main
character must change” (which is essentially an internal journey - A to B).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What I find most interesting is how Winter chooses to discuss the idea of
journey in King’s works. It is described initially as a journey from “East to
West”, and I covered this a little in my first post.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“Stephen King&amp;#58; The Art of Darkness” – Change of Approach</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/16/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-change-of-approach/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/16/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-change-of-approach/</guid><description>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m scrapping the chapter-by-chapter approach for my discussion on Douglas
Winter&amp;rsquo;s book.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Instead, I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to do a series of posts, each of which discusses what I
found to be the most critical and relevant elements in Winter&amp;rsquo;s analysis. Here&amp;rsquo;s
a list of topics I expect to cover. I&amp;rsquo;ll be spending no more than 30 minutes on
any given element to keep myself from rambling on.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The &amp;ldquo;Night Journey&amp;rdquo; (East to West)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Haunted House&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Character growth from innocence to experience (tied to the &amp;ldquo;Night Journey&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The corruption of Fairy Tale&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Vision and the writing process&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>That said, look for my first post in the next day or so. Technically, I&amp;rsquo;m on
vacation, but isn&amp;rsquo;t vacation about doing the things you enjoy most?&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“Stephen King&amp;#58; The Art of Darkness” (Ch. 3 – 4)</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/08/05/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-ch-3-4/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/08/05/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-ch-3-4/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Chapter 3 - Carrie&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In chapter 3, Winter begins his critical analysis of King&amp;rsquo;s work with &lt;em>Carrie&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here&amp;rsquo;s what I took from this chapter:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Winter considers &lt;em>Carrie&lt;/em> to be King&amp;rsquo;s most eccentric work. In part, it seems,
due to the epistolary structure.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Right from the start, King&amp;rsquo;s trademarks of &amp;ldquo;unassuming prose and truthful
characterizations&amp;rdquo; are present.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>In King&amp;rsquo;s own words, he&amp;rsquo;ll go for terror, horror, and even the gross-out. Per
Winter, &lt;em>Carrie&lt;/em> &amp;ldquo;evokes the visceral, bringing the reader down to the guy
level at which King operates best.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Winter quotes Peter Straub on the book: &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;what was really striking about it
was that it moved like the mind itself. It was an unprecedentedly direct
style&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The book deals with the loneliness of one girl.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It is a fairy tale, a warped Cinderella story.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;The Cinderella imagery is made explicit when [Carrie] loses her slippers
fleeing the ball.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Carrie&amp;rsquo;s final act of destruction &amp;ldquo;is not revenge &amp;ndash; nor is it evil.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Popular entertainment stereotypes children, but horror fiction often strives
for the inversion of innocence, &amp;ldquo;rendering children into agents of darkness
for no other reason than exploitation.&amp;rdquo; Winter cites &lt;em>The Exorcist&lt;/em> and &lt;em>The
Omen&lt;/em>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>In Carrie, the &amp;ldquo;evil lies not in Carrie White but in her tormentors &amp;ndash; and,
more important, in the traps of society and religious mania in which her
tormentors are confined.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Carrie White is, in Winter&amp;rsquo;s words, &amp;ldquo;the first of many King protagonists who
reflect his naturalist stance &amp;ndash; she starts nothing of her own free will.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>Carrie&lt;/em> is a story about the coming of age, showing the romantic side of King
and his belief in the innate goodness of children.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The coming of age in &lt;em>Carrie&lt;/em> is a journey - east to west.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>Carrie&lt;/em> also provides social commentary through a pervasive feminist element.
&amp;ldquo;The blood imagery of &lt;em>Carrie&lt;/em> has sexual significance, not as an extension of
erotic power&amp;hellip;but of feminine power.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>In contrast to the traditional fairy tale, where the heroine succeeds at her
trials and wins the kingdom, Carrie is pushed to the edge, left no alternative
but violence, and were it not for her &amp;ldquo;gift&amp;rdquo;, she would likely have failed.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>In King&amp;rsquo;s words: &amp;ldquo;The fundamental unfairness of naturalistic storytelling is
that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t really admit for much optimism&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The final horror in the book is not Carrie&amp;rsquo;s. It is Susan Snell, &amp;ldquo;who must
live in the memory of blackness and its death song.&amp;rdquo; Susan Snell survives but
to what kind of life?&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>What I took from Winter&amp;rsquo;s analysis is King&amp;rsquo;s first published novel already sets
a pattern of naturalistic storytelling, of twisted fairy tales, and that the
idea of journey is fundamental to King&amp;rsquo;s work. King&amp;rsquo;s plain style and the
naturalism are a powerful combination.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“Stephen King: The Art of Darkness” (Ch. 1-2)</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/29/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-ch-1-2/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/29/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-ch-1-2/</guid><description>&lt;p>The next book in my reading journal is &amp;ldquo;Stephen King: The Art of Darkness&amp;rdquo;, by
Douglas E. Winter. Winter&amp;rsquo;s book is a critical look at King&amp;rsquo;s work up to the
mid-80&amp;rsquo;s mixed with biographical information.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Chapter 1 - Introduction: Do the Dead Sing?&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The first chapter and introduction to the work poses the question, &amp;ldquo;Do the Dead
Sing?&amp;rdquo;. With that question, Winter brings us into the world of King by a broad
overview of some of King&amp;rsquo;s works, and an analysis of how they fit into and have
molded modern American Horror. Winter discusses some common elements found in
King&amp;rsquo;s fiction, using &amp;ldquo;The Reach&amp;rdquo; as an entry point:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“From Shadowed Places”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/23/from-shadowed-places/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/23/from-shadowed-places/</guid><description>&lt;p>There are two aspects of this piece I find as valuable models for a writer. The
first is the idea of death by inches. In my experience with horror, death come
as a relatively swift blow - maybe there&amp;rsquo;s some torture, definitely some pain,
but it is usually played out by a lot of tension and a quick end. Peter Lang has
been under severe torture for months by the time we enter the story, and it
shows through Matheson&amp;rsquo;s use of action, dialog, and description:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“Person to Person”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/22/person-to-person/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/22/person-to-person/</guid><description>&lt;p>Dialog like this is a challenge. Matheson&amp;rsquo;s main character, David Millman, is
ultimately having a conversation with himself. He&amp;rsquo;s the crazy guy who hears
voices in his head. I&amp;rsquo;ve written a couple of pieces that have this happen in
them, but I haven&amp;rsquo;t been able to pull them off so well (in my humble opinion).
Why is it that this story works but my own efforts haven&amp;rsquo;t?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I think it&amp;rsquo;s because when I&amp;rsquo;ve done it, my crazy main character sounds&amp;hellip; crazy.
I think one reason this piece is pulled off so well is that, through Millman&amp;rsquo;s
internal dialog, the reader is presented with several plausible alternatives to
him actually being crazy. The internal dialog is presented as a having a series
of explanations that all have the appearance of an external dialog - some
through technology, one as communication with the dead. All are direct dialogs -
person to person. So this internal dialog never gets old, as a fresh perspective
is presented with each new plausible explanation.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“The Funeral”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/21/the-funeral/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/21/the-funeral/</guid><description>&lt;p>What I found most useful in this story is the sense of perspective, and how the
POV character needn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily be the main character. The story is told from
Morton Silkline&amp;rsquo;s perspective - the Director of a little cut-rate funeral home.
While the story is his, I would argue that he doesn&amp;rsquo;t really experience any
change and isn&amp;rsquo;t really the main character. It&amp;rsquo;s the vampire Ludwig Asper who is
looking for a change, and ultimately receives it in the form of the funeral he
never had.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“Mad House”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/18/mad-house/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/18/mad-house/</guid><description>&lt;p>Matheson uses a great focus technique to bring the reader into this story. The
first four sections of &amp;ldquo;Mad House&amp;rdquo; are told in present tense, after which the
story switches to the usual past tense. These first four sections, which cover
only a few pages, are very special. They are tightly focused on the main
character and his anger problem. They are very action oriented, walking the
reader through several incidents of conflict between the main character and his
surroundings. We get no narration on who this guy is or why he&amp;rsquo;s so angry. We
get pure action and emotion. By the time the reader reaches the last section,
there&amp;rsquo;s a mountain of questions that have developed and drive the reader on
through the rest of the piece.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“Dress of White Silk”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/15/dress-of-white-silk/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/15/dress-of-white-silk/</guid><description>&lt;p>Telling a story from a child&amp;rsquo;s point of view is a challenge. Telling it in a
child&amp;rsquo;s language is a challenge as well. This piece was a little difficult for
me to get engaged with because of Matheson&amp;rsquo;s lack of punctuation and the poor
grammar (both intentional). This has the feel of an experimental piece.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I think that to be an effective writer at this sort of thing takes a lot of
practice. I kept thinking of Cormac McCarthy and his breaking of the rules. I
think the challenge put to the reader must be rewarded by the payoff, and in
this case, I don&amp;rsquo;t think the payoff was worth it. A good story, yes, but I think
it would have been just as effective told with more conventional grammar and
just using the child&amp;rsquo;s point of view.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“Witch War”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/14/witch-war/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2009 00:02:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/14/witch-war/</guid><description>&lt;p>Why didn&amp;rsquo;t someone tell me there were so many vignette&amp;rsquo;s in &amp;ldquo;I Am Legend&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Anyhow, this little snippet is almost poetry. It&amp;rsquo;s a great collection of images
given in clear, if abrupt, language:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Sky clearing its throat with thunder, picking and dropping long lightening
from immeasurable shoulders. Rain hushing the world, bowing the trees, pocking
earth. Square building, low, with one wall plastic.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s what really stands out to me here. Matheson&amp;rsquo;s use of imagery is
overpowering here, which is okay since there&amp;rsquo;s not much other than an intriguing
incident here. Not even a main character to speak of, nor a clear conflict other
than the generic conflict we find in any war. As a writer, the poetics of this
piece really appeal to me, and I think it&amp;rsquo;s a good example of how to work poetic
images into narrative.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“Prey”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/14/prey/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2009 00:01:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/14/prey/</guid><description>&lt;p>This vignette by Matheson gives an interesting parallel between a horrible
little Zuni fetish doll, and the power of a parent over their child. As a
reader, I enjoyed the chase and suspense of the woman being hunted by this
little hunter. It&amp;rsquo;s a cool little encounter.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What I found most valuable as a writer, though, is the phone conversation
between mother and daughter, as well as their family dynamic. Mother is
manipulative and demanding, and is preying on her daughter&amp;rsquo;s emotions. It felt a
little bizarre at first, having Matheson take us from this emotionally charged
interaction into this physically charged chase. But, I found myself hoping that
this little chase would give Amelia the strength (change her character) to stand
up to her mother and start taking control of her own life.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Undead Blog</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/11/undead-blog/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2009 00:04:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/11/undead-blog/</guid><description>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve revived my blog. It&amp;rsquo;s been dead for about a year. Poor blog.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I started a Master of Arts program in Writing Popular Fiction at Seton Hill
University at the end of June. Kismet - the first day of my first writer&amp;rsquo;s
residency was also my birthday.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Anyhow, part of the program involves reading (of course). And that requires a
reading journal. Perfect use for a blog.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Welcome back, poor little neglected blog. Welcome back.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“The Near Departed”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/11/the-near-departed/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2009 00:03:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/11/the-near-departed/</guid><description>&lt;p>Another interesting little vignette by Matheson. To be honest, though, I didn&amp;rsquo;t
find anything particularly interesting from a writer&amp;rsquo;s perspective. The dialog
is plain, there&amp;rsquo;s little action, no real sense of tension, and the ending is
standard &amp;ldquo;Twilight Zone&amp;rdquo; material.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“I Am Legend” (Ch. 17 – 21)</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/11/i-am-legend-ch-17-21/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2009 00:02:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/11/i-am-legend-ch-17-21/</guid><description>&lt;p>These are the final chapters. Matheson does a great job of continuing to create
change in Neville. He&amp;rsquo;s encountered another human who is apparently immune as
well, Ruth. He&amp;rsquo;s cold and distrustful at first, now having been in isolation for
about 3 years.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>He suddenly realized that he had become an ill-tempered and inveterate
bachelor again. He no longer thought about his wife, his child, his past life.
The present was enough.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“Buried Talents”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/11/buried-talents/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2009 00:01:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/11/buried-talents/</guid><description>&lt;p>This vignette by Richard Matheson presents an interesting technique for
escalation. It&amp;rsquo;s brief story of an odd man who plays a game at the fair, the one
where you chuck ping-pong balls into a fishbowl, and never misses.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The escalation is just that - the man never misses. It is, by nature of the
scene, repetitive, but it&amp;rsquo;s the repetition of the man&amp;rsquo;s success that builds the
story, bringing the reader along. Will he ever miss? Is he a shill? The carny
gets first annoyed, the suspicious, and finally upset as this stranger drops
ball after ball in the same fishbowl.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“I Am Legend” (Ch. 12 – 16)</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/09/i-am-legend-ch-12-16/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/09/i-am-legend-ch-12-16/</guid><description>&lt;p>Here we find Neville hitting another brick wall. He thinks he&amp;rsquo;s figured out
what&amp;rsquo;s causing the vampires - a Bacilli (germ) - but he can&amp;rsquo;t attribute all the
vampire behaviors to it. So, what does he do? Well, by this point we know
Neville pretty well - a man who, although he&amp;rsquo;s survived some pretty extreme
circumstances, falls back to the drink when things get too challenging.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Man, it&amp;rsquo;s time this guy get a new tune.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“I Am Legend” (Ch. 9 – 11)</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/07/i-am-legend-ch-9-11/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/07/i-am-legend-ch-9-11/</guid><description>&lt;p>So here we get more of Neville&amp;rsquo;s backstory, the death of his wife, his
determination to bury her instead of burn her, and the horror of her return as a
vampire. It&amp;rsquo;s interesting, but what really interested me more in these chapters
is how Matheson shows us real change in Neville.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Neville has continued sobering himself up, tackling his situation like a real
problem solver. He refers a few time to his father&amp;rsquo;s belief in the scientific
method as inspiration. It&amp;rsquo;s an interesting character development, so see Neville
set upon the library, reading and learning everything he can, teaching himself
to use a microscope, learning to understand what he&amp;rsquo;s looking at, and ultimately
coming to the conclusion that this is a virus.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“I Am Legend” (Ch. 4 – 8)</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/06/i-am-legend-ch-4-8/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/06/i-am-legend-ch-4-8/</guid><description>&lt;p>Matheson turns Neville&amp;rsquo;s character around in these chapters. At the end of
chapter 4, Neville has forgotten to wind his watch and is stuck out after dark,
not even sure what time it is. He survives the attacks, and spends the next
couple of months rebuilding his home, getting to things he&amp;rsquo;d never done (like
soundproofing the walls). He then sets about trying to figure out what he can
about the virus or plague or whatever it is that&amp;rsquo;s caused all the people to
turn.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“I Am Legend” (Ch. 1 – 3)</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/04/i-am-legend-chapt-1-3/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/04/i-am-legend-chapt-1-3/</guid><description>&lt;p>Matheson&amp;rsquo;s first three chapters do something I always find very difficult to
pull off. He managed to develop a character in isolation, without having any
benefit of dialog with another character. The description and narration combine
well to bring out poor Robert Neville&amp;rsquo;s ordinary world.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I think Matheson also does a great job of building up the attackers through
their actions (and the one who constantly taunts - &amp;ldquo;Come out, Neville!&amp;rdquo;). He
makes it through two full chapters before referring to them outright as
&amp;ldquo;vampires&amp;rdquo;, giving the reader plenty of material to work with before falling
into stereotypes of the vampire. By the time we get to the explicit statement,
we as readers have been prepared for the idea that these may be vampires, but
they&amp;rsquo;re not Vampires.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“Dance of the Dead”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/03/dance-of-the-dead/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/03/dance-of-the-dead/</guid><description>&lt;p>Richard Matheson&amp;rsquo;s short story, &amp;ldquo;Dance of the Dead&amp;rdquo;, is a fine example of
matching up pacing and action. The story opens with four college kids racing
across the plains in a &amp;ldquo;Rotor-Motors Convertible, Model C, 1997&amp;rdquo;. The kids are
engaged in drinking, drugs, and sex as they head to Saint Louis to catch a
&amp;ldquo;loopy&amp;rdquo; show.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Needle quivering at 130, two 5-mph notches from the gauge&amp;rsquo;s end. A sudden dip!
Their young frames jolted and the thrown-up laughter of three was windswept
into night. Around a curve, darting up and down a hill, flashing across a
leveled plain &amp;ndash; an ebony bullet skimming the earth.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>My First Paying Market!</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2008/07/08/my-first-paying-market/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2008/07/08/my-first-paying-market/</guid><description>&lt;p>I got up this morning, groggy as hell. Yeah, getting up at 4 am will do that to
ya. But, it&amp;rsquo;s paying off! In my inbox was my first acceptance notice! My short
story, Gray, is to be published in the January 2009 edition of
&lt;a href="http://www.necrotictissue.com" title="Necrotic Tissue.">Necrotic Tissue&lt;/a>!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sweeeeet&amp;hellip; I&amp;rsquo;m going back to bed.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Colors</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2007/08/24/colors/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2007/08/24/colors/</guid><description>&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-poem" data-lang="poem">you sense my hesitation.
 good.

This is the color of DREAM

we are children, unseeing
 we open our eye
 unlocking the verse and meter
 of the universe.

This is the color of FORGET

it is here
 look closer.
 this is the color

This is the color of SAD

baby girl, club-footed
 opens her eyes.
 pressed between hot sun
 and rough mountain
 welcomed to the world
 by no one.

This is the color of GREED

whatever is written here
 it is not enough.

This is the color of LOVE

one plump drop
 sneaks from a fang.

This is the color of DREAMS

one by one
 we close our eyes
 no longer children.
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre></description></item><item><title>Wednesday</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2007/08/14/wednesday/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2007/08/14/wednesday/</guid><description>&lt;p>I hum and beep at my master, but he does not listen. He pounds on my keys
furiously, typing out insubstantial things, embedding himself in the abstract.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I creak and moan. I shout to him, &amp;ldquo;Go outside! Go play! It&amp;rsquo;s too nice to sit
here all day!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>He doesn&amp;rsquo;t hear, just continues typing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I shrug my shoulders.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I am Wednesday.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>incense</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2007/05/21/incense/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 May 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2007/05/21/incense/</guid><description>&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-poem" data-lang="poem">fresh smoke
 squirms through
 our sacred window,
 pierces yesterday&amp;#39;s angel

those words, salt
 your voice, awake
 my flesh, dried
 a raw monopoly of god
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre></description></item><item><title>wet bug</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2007/05/12/wet-bug/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 May 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2007/05/12/wet-bug/</guid><description>&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-poem" data-lang="poem">squirming through
 the marbled world

when you remember words
 remember the copper tang,
 the smoky perfume,
 the sad, warm woman

your work must be
 porcelain steel rythms
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre></description></item><item><title>translucent prisoner</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2007/05/09/translucent-prisoner/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 May 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2007/05/09/translucent-prisoner/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.davidlday.com/images/imported/2007/05/translucent-prisoner.jpg" title="Translucent Prisoner">&lt;img src="https://www.davidlday.com/images/imported/2007/05/translucent-prisoner.jpg" alt="Translucent Prisoner">&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-poem" data-lang="poem">their wild steel universe
 surrounds him

broken through sex,
 velvet worry - once live -
 now devoured color

perhaps, sister, you listen -
 stiff lipped laugh, trembling

explore them, pick and haunt,
 time stream pooling
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="original-images">Original Images&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>[
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Image:Achi_Tryptichon.jpg&amp;amp;oldid=44704684">Achi Tryptichon&lt;/a>
]&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Image:AbuGhraibAbuse11.jpg&amp;amp;oldid=16452642">AbuGraibAbuse11&lt;/a>
]&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Image:AbuGhraibAbuse14.jpg&amp;amp;oldid=16452645">AbuGraibAbuse14&lt;/a>
]&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Image:Forgetmenotflower.JPG&amp;amp;oldid=85671563">ForgetMeNotFlower&lt;/a>
]&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[
&lt;a href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?title=Image:A_Galvanised_Corpse.jpg&amp;amp;oldid=2715939">A Galvanized Corpse&lt;/a>
]&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Chernobyl and Prypiat</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2007/04/05/chernobyl_prypiat/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Apr 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2007/04/05/chernobyl_prypiat/</guid><description>&lt;p>A great disaster. For a novel I started working on in October 2006, I started
doing some research. There&amp;rsquo;s a portion of it that takes place in an old,
abandoned city, one that had been left in destitution for centuries, so I was
looking around for theories on what happens to a modern city when left to the
forces of nature. To my shame, I had forgotten about the Chernobyl disaster. In
my research, I rediscovered it.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>End of NaNoWriMo</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/12/02/end-of-nanowrimo/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Dec 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/12/02/end-of-nanowrimo/</guid><description>&lt;p>NaNoWriMo wrapped up, of course, on November 30. How&amp;rsquo;d I do? I wound up with a
word count of 48,459. Not the goal of NaNoWriMo, I know. But, it satisfies me
that with an outline, and setting aside a few hours a night for writing 5 out of
7 days a week, I can make some tremendous progress towards a novel. Personally,
after doing this the second time, I&amp;rsquo;ve come to agree with
&lt;a href="http://www.antimuse.org/blog/?p=25" title="AntiBlog">these wise words&lt;/a> - I&amp;rsquo;d rather
have spent the time writing something worth reading than cranking out 50,000
words worth of crap.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>NaNoWriMo</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/11/01/nanowrimo/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/11/01/nanowrimo/</guid><description>&lt;p>Today kicks off NaNoWriMo. I&amp;rsquo;ve completed most of my novel&amp;rsquo;s outline, and I
cranked out over 1500 words in just a few hours. The outline thing seems to have
gotten me off to a great start! My writing came easily, I didn&amp;rsquo;t have to debate
plot lines, or wonder where the hell I&amp;rsquo;m going with it - all I had to do now was
write the scenes I&amp;rsquo;ve already laid out.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Preparing for NaNoWriMo</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/10/17/preparing-for-nanowrimo/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Oct 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/10/17/preparing-for-nanowrimo/</guid><description>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m actually preparing myself for NaNoWriMo this year. I suppose it&amp;rsquo;s really
just a coincidence, but I&amp;rsquo;m creating an outline for my novel, &amp;ldquo;The Secret of
Kingship&amp;rdquo;. I finished reading Robert McKee&amp;rsquo;s book, &amp;ldquo;Story&amp;rdquo;, and it has inspired
me. It truly gave me a better understanding of story telling in the modern age.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Anyhow, I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on an actual outline, character dossiers, and other
such stuff for a week or so now. And I&amp;rsquo;m going into this feeling very
well-prepared. I guess we&amp;rsquo;ll see, but I think when it comes down to it, good
writing is not an accident. Good writing is planned. Maybe not down to the
smallest detail, but it is planned. One of my (new) favorite quotes from McKee&amp;rsquo;s
book is:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Sin of Self-Publishing</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/10/06/the-sin-of-self-publishing/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/10/06/the-sin-of-self-publishing/</guid><description>&lt;p>It seems to me that self-publishing has an awful reputation in the literary
community. I think the view is that if you&amp;rsquo;re not good enough to get picked up
by a major magazine or publishing house, then you&amp;rsquo;re just not worth reading.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, we see more and more in other arts that self-publishing and promoting
can break the industry barrier. And, in my opinion, the independently funded and
promoted works in many ways exceed the quality of the mainstream channels.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Becoming</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/10/05/becoming/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/10/05/becoming/</guid><description>&lt;p>A young lawyer joins a new firm. Shortly after, he begins to undergo some
bizarre physiological changes. He loses his appetite, is unable to drink much of
anything, and has a host of flu-like symptoms.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Not long after this begins, he receives a package - no return address, no
identifying marks. The post markings on it are in a foreign language and
indecipherable. Inside he finds an unusual ring, pure silver, fashioned in the
shape of a triangle with the relief image of folded hands inside of it.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Asylum Angels</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/08/20/asylum-angels/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/08/20/asylum-angels/</guid><description>&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-poem" data-lang="poem">Belief in the moon,
 where we end
 abated and objecting,
 cold distance setting inch upon historical inch.

We hastily practice solitude,
 overcast angels in sheepskin jackets,
 limiting the rolling offenses
 unpaid to Sacred Support.

We are fainting angels,
 angels, cold and distant,
 wrapping flies in bullets,
 the sung grave unconcerned.

Cease wont, asylum angels.
 Awaken Atlas and flee cleverness.
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre></description></item><item><title>Partial Meal</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/08/17/partial-meal/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/08/17/partial-meal/</guid><description>&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-poem" data-lang="poem">Flesh-eating hearts
 nurtured on line-soup
 nurse ivory anguish
 that is bidden thirsty for us.

Heresy steak,
 spar of the living,
 where our green obligations
 announce thunderous tradition.

Coal redresses discontent
 implication,
 shudders resistance,
 a dizzy unseen statement.

Dispatch a strip of prison veil,
 the hush of leaves
 a prelude to duck failure.

Lunch,
 that obstructed, devoted meal.
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre></description></item><item><title>Sensenbrenner Park</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/08/14/sensenbrenner-park/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Aug 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/08/14/sensenbrenner-park/</guid><description>&lt;p>An old man, used up by his years of corporate loyalty. He has spent each evening
leaving work late, stopping by a fountain, tossing a coin in. No wishes, no
prayers, just a donation. Now, his retirement eve, the end of an uneventful day
with the obligatory cake and cards, he stops at the fountain one last time. It
is later than usual, nearly midnight, and he is alone by the fountain.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>RV dust</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/08/11/rv-dust/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/08/11/rv-dust/</guid><description>&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-poem" data-lang="poem">Hide desperation
 contained from wanting illusionary
 knowing life from memory

As manifested sounds
 with soft chamber non-existence

behold, my own wanting
 of another mirror reality
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre></description></item><item><title>wikshun</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/08/08/wikshun/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Aug 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/08/08/wikshun/</guid><description>&lt;p>I have an idea&amp;hellip;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Wiki&amp;rsquo;s have become awfully big, and they&amp;rsquo;re great at semantically linking
information together. However, they&amp;rsquo;re most suited towards documentation and
fact gathering. I&amp;rsquo;ve seen one site -
&lt;a href="http://novelas.wikia.com/" title="The Fiction Wikia">The Fiction Wikia&lt;/a> - that tries
to apply the wiki concept to story telling, but I think it has several
shortcomings. The most notable is that it forces each and every author on the
site to use the same license, the
&lt;a href="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html" title="Gnu Free Documentation License">GNU Free Documentation License&lt;/a>,
which is great for information sharing, but is in my opinion not well suited to
the fiction writer. In my opinion, the Creative Commons licenses are much more
appropriate, and provide the freedom and flexibility needed for sharing
fictional work.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Mirror</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/07/24/mirror/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Jul 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/07/24/mirror/</guid><description>&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-poem" data-lang="poem">Sublime ripples shadow purgatory wanting.
 This time mirrors my silence.

Wanting and consumed,
 Sanguine waters rushing,
 My spirit wades to be freed.

A frozen end.
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre></description></item><item><title>Unforgotten</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/08/07/unforgotten/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Jul 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/08/07/unforgotten/</guid><description>&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-poem" data-lang="poem">Time conducting desperatio
 running sorrow of knowing

illusory meaning
 traversing orchestral mirrors

touch destiny
 contained within
 a self made mirror of defiance

behold a lending of meaning
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre></description></item><item><title>Distraction</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/07/13/distraction/</link><pubDate>Thu, 13 Jul 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/07/13/distraction/</guid><description>&lt;p>The world surrounds us with distractions. Television is a particularly sinister
form, and I&amp;rsquo;m only lately coming to realize its actual power over people. Try
sitting in a room with a television on and doing something else - something like
read a book or (as I&amp;rsquo;ve often tried) writing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It doesn&amp;rsquo;t work. We are drawn to it - it stimulates us more than most other
readily accessible forms of entertainment. What happens to a person when he
slowly comes to realize how much he truly has been distracted by television? An
awaking, a stripping away of a life he thought he had, a dawning of the futility
of his own existence. Imagine living a life, and only towards the end
discovering that all the memories, all the hopes and dreams, were all borrowed
paraphernalia, all loaned to you from the entertainment industry. And imagine
realizing that the only true person to blame is yourself - you permitted
yourself to spend a life in a semi-hypnotic trace, and it&amp;rsquo;s much too late to
reverse the effects.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Institutionalized</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/25/institutionalized/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/25/institutionalized/</guid><description>&lt;p>I watched &lt;a href="http://imdb.com/title/tt0111161/">The Shawshank Redemption&lt;/a> tonight.
Not the first time I&amp;rsquo;ve seen it - and I had read the short story before the
movie came out. Both are fine works. In the movie, Morgan Freeman&amp;rsquo;s character,
&amp;lsquo;Red&amp;rsquo;, gives this little speech about how one of the other characters has been
in so long, he&amp;rsquo;s become institutionalized. In essence, it&amp;rsquo;s what happens to a
person who has been in prison so long, they stop knowing how to be valuable
outside the prison setting.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Ghosts are crazy</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/22/ghosts-are-crazy/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/22/ghosts-are-crazy/</guid><description>&lt;p>I can&amp;rsquo;t remember where I heard this, but recently, I heard something that may
seem obvious to most, but had totally escaped me. The reason we&amp;rsquo;re afraid of
ghosts is that they&amp;rsquo;re lost souls, they&amp;rsquo;re all crazy because they&amp;rsquo;re trapped
here - someplace they shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be. And we instinctively know that - that since
they are trapped, caught and bound to a place that is in opposition of what they
have become, they are driven insane.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Abbey of Delusion</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/21/abbey-of-delusion/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/21/abbey-of-delusion/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.davidlday.com/images/imported/2007/03/broken_abbey.jpg" alt="Broken Abbey">&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-poem" data-lang="poem">I built my self an Abbey of delusion content
 with angles, sharp and thick; a discharge of underground ink.

I came upon a downcast flood of commercial recipes,
 dawning thanks to the fool who juggles an excess meal.

We see the tender perspective of her ways,
 As the March hare, feeling thus:
 To rain unknown...
 To murder the threshold bricks...
 To subjective patient breaks of thick deep...
 To label (in murmurs) the deep...

They angle fetch the last,
 otherwise heaving simplex ingress.
 They angle fetch
 an otherwise deposit to decisiveness.

Woman leader,
 owing white to description...
 owing black to the objective slab...
 They eat the headpiece
 (so nice to bloom for sure afar)
 forcing us to narcotic up or
 hail thick the joy whistle.

Thick and fading hail, his fade bare pursuit.
 Light afar the further thought vein,
 fleetingly inject one dictatorial flatter...
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre></description></item><item><title>Cabbie</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/20/cabbie/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/20/cabbie/</guid><description>&lt;p>After having the worst day of his life, an unscrupulous New Yorker has a
difficult time making his way home. He is repeatedly lost and abused, and is
haunted throughout the night by a single, reappearing cabby that frightens him.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Tension</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/14/tension/</link><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/14/tension/</guid><description>&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-poem" data-lang="poem">Apollo&amp;#39;s fissured time,
 muted and screened by circumstance.

This silky night of tears
 eclipses the eye in shuttered laughter.

Delicious tragedy,
 life&amp;#39;s movement a conflict
 of fractured author and masqued audience.
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre></description></item><item><title>Magic Baby</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/12/magic-baby/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/12/magic-baby/</guid><description>&lt;p>This one is actually my wife&amp;rsquo;s idea.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This couple has this baby. The baby is very in tune to his/her parents, and it
can pick up on what they wish for. It begins granting their wishes. Sounds a
little weird, but I remember reading once that one of the Native American tribes
believes (or believed) that we are born with knowledge of the language of the
gods, and that we forget it as we grow up, forgetting completely by age 4.
Interesting&amp;hellip;.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>station</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/11/station/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/11/station/</guid><description>&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-poem" data-lang="poem">inhaling a starless breath

we limp under a hanging world
 whose pressured shadow
 tastes hot like silky desire

existence kissed by imaging
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre></description></item><item><title>Chaplain of Fabulous Paper</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/10/chaplain-of-fabulous-paper/</link><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/10/chaplain-of-fabulous-paper/</guid><description>&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-poem" data-lang="poem">Put out the eyes of foresight,
 which underneath taught torrential calm
 despite the thrilling clear acumen.
 Take ease in the transparent
 steady slumber which it allies like
 privileged unmasked liquid,
 binding sanity to impulse,
 a manifold chord.

Demonic rum,
 harmless to the churchman&amp;#39;s skeleton,
 that rabbit of relief and sovereign egotist,
 loops prejudice and indexes possibilities
 preying on resident thoughts
 which tingle with ill passing.
 Enter the transfusion of flashing
 standstills germane to grasping,
 leaving us to stare at appealing refractions.

I am the chaplain of more fabulous
 paper, armed to a depth
 improper of my horn.

Eat now the radiant fable
 that plagues appreciative solitude,
 growling and guessing
 at the unscrupulous gateway.
 Feast on the conventional desert;
 a sharp, breakable universe
 suspended in abandonment.

Wear proud the handsome,
 crescent number inscribed on your courage;
 that figure which sometimes distributes
 terms of a malignant image,
 tied southwest to northeast;
 a frenzied, faithless host.

Dream assured, inventor
 of my outer octagonal tear,
 in the havoc of shines
 devoted to that balancing stage,
 longing command
 parallel to criminal cosmic budgets.

Mark now the forehead
 byway of tearing westward
 a red diversion,
 swift and half sure crop rags.

Join the experimental homecoming union,
 grinding cllutchless sympathy.
 Bleed of the surroundings
 that loop and bind our feet.
 Battle the occasional barbarian
 dream in curious structure.

Critical routes
 pass disgusting guardians
 and common horror lust.
 Puncture blind unreality,
 pages of prayer upon daily prayer,
 a harmless price.

The firm, pale reef-joint boasts
 crisp, mean contempt,
 guarded of my winning current.
 Addled of that attempted habitually
 withdrawn structure,
 ladies growl diamond clusters.

Today darts alert,
 waking the past with vapor
 flash sacrifice cries.
 Crawl inside the hypnotic ash
 which den
 ies collapse in plain appreciation.
 Bone rough and wounded glare
 wilderness cunning.

Temperament counters a
 leaky social class.
 Hearing good never grew
 almighty author of wounds.
 Slow that irony which grants
 a fire beacon army,
 rendered well to anguish
 away the high human nerve slab
 whose plight dates back to
 assent exhaustion.

Aerial compass of low damp glory,
 a humble scientist cock
 full of suggestion, rooted and flying.

Shiver the roar of gray
 floating assemblage glee.
 Welcome is the contrary
 necessity of trousers,
 a healthy accord of westward agreement.
 Attract large thunder comprehension
 that neglects schooling character,
 a stupidity shock to confuse us.
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre></description></item><item><title>The Cat Ladies</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/09/the-cat-ladies/</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/09/the-cat-ladies/</guid><description>&lt;p>An animal rescue group is clearing out a house where a woman and her elderly
mother live in extremely unhealthy conditions, along with about 100 cats. What
they find deep beneath the 50 years worth of accumulated junk and mounds of cat
excrement is much more than any of them expected.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Stalks of Faith</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/08/stalks-of-faith/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/08/stalks-of-faith/</guid><description>&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-poem" data-lang="poem">A helpless yellow disciple of anger,
 precariously fluttering against the concrete earth.

Preachers and brethren,
 hung by the umbilical stalk of faith,
 shake and chortle.

The wavering spine of desire,
 snapped and severed
 by the coarse sparks of flesh.

Red tenderness is found
 by flames of will.
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre></description></item><item><title>1000 Words</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/07/1000-words/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/07/1000-words/</guid><description>&lt;p>1000 words per day. If you write 1000 words per day, you can crank out a lot of
writing. I&amp;rsquo;ve seen indications around that a writer&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;apprenticeship&amp;rsquo; should
amount to one million written words. If you can do 1000 words a day, then an
apprenticeship amounts to about 3 years.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I have no idea if that stuff about an &amp;lsquo;apprenticeship&amp;rsquo; is true, if it really
takes one million words before a writer achieves that almost mindless level of
production to consider themselves a writer. What I do know is that 1000 words a
day is a good target for me. It&amp;rsquo;ll get me cranking out a short story per week.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Story Lines – Introduction</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/06/story-lines-introduction/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/06/story-lines-introduction/</guid><description>&lt;p>Every story stems from a crisis. As readers, we are most interested in the
struggles of our fellow humans. Our interest is most easily captured by bad
news, stress, conflict. Not that the outcomes must be bad &amp;ndash; on the contrary, we
love stories that depict triumph in the face of adversity. But the thing that
most easily grabs us is when tension, crisis, and turmoil erupt into everyday
life.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Abandon</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/05/abandon/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/05/abandon/</guid><description>&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-poem" data-lang="poem">Mildly blamed abandon,
 a vanishing madness
 poignant over the boundlessness
 of hot yard, pagan-hearted discontent;
 of sweet man, with verbatim extreme control.

Mighty punishment out of turn
 casting the bound shrine,
 a bygone tomb,
 where indeed electricity
 arcs truly their legend.

Regional bloody faith
 itemizes the witnesses.
 Grave-wide perceptible excuses
 condemn religious humility
 with calculated infected ejaculations.

Weakness wrought out of structure
 holding dearly
 to the offending horn.
 Faltering skins swallow anything,
 downcast moonlight their restraint.
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre></description></item><item><title>Start of a new day</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/04/start-of-a-new-day/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2006/06/04/start-of-a-new-day/</guid><description>&lt;p>I set up this new site today. It&amp;rsquo;s my first step in publicizing myself as a
writer. My wife recently gave birth to our first son (also David L. Day), and
during the course of her pregnancy, as well as the three weeks I was off after
the delivery, I came to realize something. I want my son to learn a lot of
things about life, and one in particular is that he should never give up on
pursing his dreams.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>“Stephen King&amp;#58; The Art of Darkness” – The Haunted House</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/28/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-the-haunted-house/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/28/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-the-haunted-house/</guid><description>&lt;p>Another element Winter discusses in his analysis of King is the haunted house.
What strikes me as most interesting with this is that, while I think Winter does
a good job of identifying the various &amp;lsquo;haunted houses&amp;rsquo; in King&amp;rsquo;s works, he never
seems to talk about what the idea of &amp;lsquo;setting as character&amp;rsquo; directly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For context, Winter identifies the following as noteworthy &amp;lsquo;haunted houses&amp;rsquo;:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The Martsen House in &lt;em>&amp;lsquo;Salem&amp;rsquo;s Lot&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Overlook Hotel in &lt;em>The Shining&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Agincourt Hotel in &lt;em>The Talisman&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Dark Tower in &lt;em>The Dark Tower&lt;/em> series *&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The last one is my own addition. At the time of Winter&amp;rsquo;s writing, The Dark Tower
was still in its infancy, with only the first book having been published. And,
as I look back over King&amp;rsquo;s works, there&amp;rsquo;s definitely other minor places
(settings) that would also qualify as &amp;lsquo;haunted houses&amp;rsquo;, but these four represent
to me the most important aspect.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>