<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>everyman on David L. Day</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/tags/everyman/</link><description>Recent content in everyman on David L. Day</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2012 03:33:40 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.davidlday.com/tags/everyman/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Sleeping Like an Idiot: Week 7 - Charts!</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/09/24/sleeping-like-an-idiot-week-7-charts/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2012 03:33:40 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/09/24/sleeping-like-an-idiot-week-7-charts/</guid><description>I managed to pull together four charts to help demonstrate progress. I took a cue from The Hacker’s Diet and used a 20-Day moving average to get trends. In each chart the actual measure is in blue and the trend is in orange. For now I just used a Simple Moving Average since the charts are just to get a sense of how things are going and aren’t meant to give highly accurate measures.</description></item><item><title>Sleep Experiment: Week 6</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/09/18/sleep-experiment-week-6/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Sep 2012 07:28:56 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/09/18/sleep-experiment-week-6/</guid><description>I’m a couple of days behind in putting this up, mainly because I was hoping to get some charts put together from my Zeo. The charts provided through its software are nice, but they’re not really showing what I want, so I have a little bit of work to do still.
Remember, I’m doing an Everyman sleep schedule, which involves a major sleep event at night and multiple naps during the day.</description></item><item><title>Reintroducing the Sleep Experiment: 5 Weeks @ 5 Hours a Night</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/09/09/reintroducing-the-sleep-experiment-5-weeks-5/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2012 08:42:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/09/09/reintroducing-the-sleep-experiment-5-weeks-5/</guid><description>About five weeks ago I posted about the sleep experiment I was undertaking. I haven’t been as diligent as I would like in recording results via blog, so I’m going to do some catching up here and make the effort more frequently.
Yesterday I caught up on the progress of Handy Andy Pandy—this dude’s an inspiration for me. I also reread my [first post]({% post_url 2012-07-21-a-writers-experiment-with-sleep %}) and realized it didn’t actually share details on what I’m doing very well.</description></item></channel></rss>