<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Creativity on David L. Day</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/tags/creativity/</link><description>Recent content in Creativity on David L. Day</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Jul 2012 16:56:04 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.davidlday.com/tags/creativity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>A Writer's Experiment with Sleep</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/07/21/a-writers-experiment-with-sleep/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Jul 2012 16:56:04 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/07/21/a-writers-experiment-with-sleep/</guid><description>&lt;p>Last week I started a new experiment in writing, one that I hope will both boost
productivity and creativity. It’s not your typical experiment, though. I’m not
going to stand on my head while I write, or use prompt cards, or any other fancy
tools I don’t already use. I’m going to change something much more fundamental
about my writing habit. I’m changing my sleep. Okay, not so exciting, but I
think it’s a promising approach. You see, I’m already fairly comfortable with my
writing. It’s not perfect, but it’s workable and I think I’m at a point where
the best thing I can do to improve is to simply keep writing. I’ve done the
workshops, I graduated from Seton Hill’s awesome Writing Popular Fiction
graduate program, and I have a trusted group of critique partners and beta
readers. And I’m reading, something I always did but now I select what I read
with more intent on developing a sense of the genres I work in. What’s left?
Well, it’s just a matter of time. Something we’re all a little short on. I’m
determined to reduce the number of hours I spend in bed—sleeping, that is. We
all want more hours in the day, and I think it’s possible. We spend something
like 8 hours in bed each night, 1/3 of our day, and I’m not so sure it’s
necessary. A couple years ago, after having our second child, I embarked on a
similar journey. Everyone knows that having a kid is typically an exercise in
sleep deprivation, so I picked up this thing called a WakeMate to help me track
how much sleep I was getting. I’m not going to review it, but suffice to say the
thing wasn’t for me. In retrospect I should have realized I wouldn’t like it—I
hate wearing watches or anything on my wrist for that matter. So I used it for a
few months then gave up. Recently I came across a new device, the Zeo Sleep
Manager Pro+, and so far it’s awesome. It’s a headband instead of a wristband,
works with my iPhone, and gives pretty good stats on my sleep. I’m still trying
to figure out how I can share graphs and such. When I do, I’ll start posting
them here. Where am I going with this? I’ve always hated sleeping. Not the
actual act, but having to lie in bed for 8 hours straight. Don’t get me wrong, I
can and do sleep for that long, but somehow I always feel cheated out of time.
And after using the Zeo for a few days I’m beginning to see a reason for this
feeling (or maybe I’m rationalizing, but whatever). Zeo breaks your sleep down
into 4 catagories: Wake, REM, Light, and Deep.What’s interesting is that Zeo
discounts your time in Light Sleep. Wake, REM, and Deep all contribute to how
well you slept on any given night, but time in Light Sleep seems to make little
to no difference. Before using this thing, I would typically sleep six or seven
hours a night. And even though I would get up pretty early to write, lately my
writing’s been a struggle. This past week, I tried sleeping only five hours a
night with two 20-minute power naps during the day. So far so good. My
productivity was stellar (for me), with two days @ 1500 words, and the rest
@ 1000. On Friday, I let myself get a ‘normal’ night’s sleep (for me, that’s six
hours), and according to Zeo I slept better than most men my age can in eight
hours, with serious amounts of time in both REM and Deep sleep. And I felt great
in the morning. I’m not going to turn this into a sleep blog, but I will
periodically post things about my progress. My next goal is to figure out how to
share charts so you can actually see more details. Why am I sharing this? I
think too often when we struggle in our endeavors, be it writing or anything
else, we often overlook that possibility that changing something outside that
endeavor may help things improve. We, like the universe, are a complex
interaction of events and experiences. For me, writing is intimately connected
to my dreaming and sleep, and so I’m chasing the theory that altering something
in one will affect the other. My next experiment will deal with lucid dreaming.
But it’ll have to wait for two things: I reach a comfortable compressed sleeping
pattern, and the remee is released.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>