<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>writing on David L. Day</title><link>https://davidlday.github.io/tags/writing/</link><description>Recent content in writing on David L. Day</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://davidlday.github.io/tags/writing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Diversity in the Reading List</title><link>https://davidlday.github.io/posts-archive/2016/03/08/diversity-in-reading/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://davidlday.github.io/posts-archive/2016/03/08/diversity-in-reading/</guid><description>Happy International Women&amp;rsquo;s Day!
In honor of, I&amp;rsquo;d like to share my reading list from 2015. Except for 2 non-fiction books I read for work, all of these works were written by women authors. Take a quick look:
You by Caroline Kepnes Fuse by Julianna Baggott Burn by Julianna Baggott A Discovery of Witches by Deborah Harkness Over Sea, Under Stone by Susan Cooper The Dark is Rising by Susan Cooper Shadow of Night by Deborah Harkness Greenwitch by Susan Cooper The Cognitive Style of Power Point by Edward R.</description></item><item><title>Getting Back Into It</title><link>https://davidlday.github.io/posts-archive/2016/01/10/getting-back-into-it/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://davidlday.github.io/posts-archive/2016/01/10/getting-back-into-it/</guid><description>Nearly four years ago, in early 2012, I started taking Taekwondo. I was overweight, out of shape, but my oldest minion had been taking classes for a year plus and had just turned old enough to start doing family classes. So I buckled down, drank plenty of water, tried not to smoke so much and gave it a shot.
I didn&amp;rsquo;t just show up to class with him one day, though.</description></item><item><title>Sweet Baby Cthulhu! I've Been Infected!</title><link>https://davidlday.github.io/posts-archive/2012/10/23/sweet-baby-cthulhu-ive-been-infected/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2012 22:46:32 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://davidlday.github.io/posts-archive/2012/10/23/sweet-baby-cthulhu-ive-been-infected/</guid><description>The hip and talented writer Stephanie Wytovich tagged me in a game of author infection. The rules are simple. Search your work in progress for the first use of “look”. Copy and paste that paragraph and the ones immediately before and after into a blog post. Then, like all good chain letters, tag five other authors. Wash, rinse, repeat.
This is from the nearly finished first draft of my novel The Galvanized Man.</description></item><item><title>Look, Ma, No Word Processor!</title><link>https://davidlday.github.io/posts-archive/2012/10/20/look-ma-no-word-processor/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Oct 2012 10:15:05 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://davidlday.github.io/posts-archive/2012/10/20/look-ma-no-word-processor/</guid><description>A couple of weeks ago I posted about how I needed to get back to planning. My current project—a novel that’s probably too complex, but fun to write—stalled and I couldn’t find a way back into the story. I needed to put the word processor aside and revisit the fundamental structure of the story.
I also mentioned in that post how I like to use index cards for planning my DIY projects around the house.</description></item><item><title>No More Sleepy Posts</title><link>https://davidlday.github.io/posts-archive/2012/10/11/no-more-sleepy-posts/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2012 06:05:55 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://davidlday.github.io/posts-archive/2012/10/11/no-more-sleepy-posts/</guid><description>Just a quick announcement I no longer plan to blog regularly about my polyphasic sleep. I have a few different reasons, but the biggest is that frankly I don’t think my personal experiment is all that interesting. I’m still interested, but I can’t get all that excited about it. My sleep data goes back to the middle of July, and what I noticed is that even when I sleep in, I usually only sleep about six hours.</description></item><item><title>A Little Bit of Planning...</title><link>https://davidlday.github.io/posts-archive/2012/10/08/a-little-bit-of-planning/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2012 04:59:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://davidlday.github.io/posts-archive/2012/10/08/a-little-bit-of-planning/</guid><description>I had an epiphany yesterday while working on a “weekend project” that’s taken several months. You see, there are no more real weekend projects in our home since we had our second son. My wife and I are lucky to get five minutes to ourselves on any given day, which is more than fine since we love our boys and love hanging out with them. But it sure makes it tough to indulge our DIY tendencies.</description></item><item><title>Sleeping Like an Idiot: Week 7 - Charts!</title><link>https://davidlday.github.io/posts-archive/2012/09/24/sleeping-like-an-idiot-week-7-charts/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2012 03:33:40 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://davidlday.github.io/posts-archive/2012/09/24/sleeping-like-an-idiot-week-7-charts/</guid><description>I managed to pull together four charts to help demonstrate progress. I took a cue from The Hacker’s Diet and used a 20-Day moving average to get trends. In each chart the actual measure is in blue and the trend is in orange. For now I just used a Simple Moving Average since the charts are just to get a sense of how things are going and aren’t meant to give highly accurate measures.</description></item><item><title>Sleep Experiment: Week 6</title><link>https://davidlday.github.io/posts-archive/2012/09/18/sleep-experiment-week-6/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Sep 2012 07:28:56 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://davidlday.github.io/posts-archive/2012/09/18/sleep-experiment-week-6/</guid><description>I’m a couple of days behind in putting this up, mainly because I was hoping to get some charts put together from my Zeo. The charts provided through its software are nice, but they’re not really showing what I want, so I have a little bit of work to do still.
Remember, I’m doing an Everyman sleep schedule, which involves a major sleep event at night and multiple naps during the day.</description></item><item><title>Reintroducing the Sleep Experiment: 5 Weeks @ 5 Hours a Night</title><link>https://davidlday.github.io/posts-archive/2012/09/09/reintroducing-the-sleep-experiment-5-weeks-5/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2012 08:42:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://davidlday.github.io/posts-archive/2012/09/09/reintroducing-the-sleep-experiment-5-weeks-5/</guid><description>About five weeks ago I posted about the sleep experiment I was undertaking. I haven’t been as diligent as I would like in recording results via blog, so I’m going to do some catching up here and make the effort more frequently.
Yesterday I caught up on the progress of Handy Andy Pandy—this dude’s an inspiration for me. I also reread my [first post]({% post_url 2012-07-21-a-writers-experiment-with-sleep %}) and realized it didn’t actually share details on what I’m doing very well.</description></item><item><title>How to Succeed as a Writer</title><link>https://davidlday.github.io/posts-archive/2012/08/10/how-to-succeed-as-a-writer/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Aug 2012 06:45:51 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://davidlday.github.io/posts-archive/2012/08/10/how-to-succeed-as-a-writer/</guid><description>A couple of days ago, Jeff VanderMeer posted an articulate and insightful piece on the future of publishing. It’s not typical among the current flood of posts and opinions about where we’re going or what the next hot thing is. Rather, Jeff gets to the heart of what he believes to be a real problem today with the advice and predictions being touted in the writing community.
Go read his post if you haven’t already.</description></item><item><title>A Writer's Experiment with Sleep</title><link>https://davidlday.github.io/posts-archive/2012/07/21/a-writers-experiment-with-sleep/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Jul 2012 16:56:04 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://davidlday.github.io/posts-archive/2012/07/21/a-writers-experiment-with-sleep/</guid><description>Last week I started a new experiment in writing, one that I hope will both boost productivity and creativity. It’s not your typical experiment, though. I’m not going to stand on my head while I write, or use prompt cards, or any other fancy tools I don’t already use. I’m going to change something much more fundamental about my writing habit. I’m changing my sleep. Okay, not so exciting, but I think it’s a promising approach.</description></item></channel></rss>