<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Writing on David L. Day</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/tags/writing/</link><description>Recent content in Writing on David L. Day</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.davidlday.com/tags/writing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Diversity in the Reading List</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2016/03/08/diversity-in-reading/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2016/03/08/diversity-in-reading/</guid><description>&lt;p>Happy &lt;a href="http://www.internationalwomensday.com/">International Women&amp;rsquo;s Day&lt;/a>!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In honor of, I&amp;rsquo;d like to share my reading list from 2015. Except for 2
non-fiction books I read for work, all of these works were written by women
authors. Take a quick look:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/20821614-you">You&lt;/a> by Caroline Kepnes&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/9752754-fuse">Fuse&lt;/a> by Julianna Baggott&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18984702-burn">Burn&lt;/a> by Julianna Baggott&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/11468955-a-discovery-of-witches">A Discovery of Witches&lt;/a>
by Deborah Harkness&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/11312.Over_Sea_Under_Stone">Over Sea, Under Stone&lt;/a>
by Susan Cooper&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/210329.The_Dark_is_Rising">The Dark is Rising&lt;/a>
by Susan Cooper&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/16171223-shadow-of-night">Shadow of Night&lt;/a>
by Deborah Harkness&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/24963.Greenwitch">Greenwitch&lt;/a> by Susan
Cooper&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/742719.The_Cognitive_Style_of_Power_Point">The Cognitive Style of Power Point&lt;/a>
by Edward R. Tufte&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/17744.The_Visual_Display_of_Quantitative_Information">The Visual Display of Quantitative Information&lt;/a>
by Edward R. Tufte&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/745955.The_Grey_King">The Grey King&lt;/a> by
Susan Cooper&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/16054217-the-book-of-life">The Book of Life&lt;/a>
by Deborah Harkness&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18635000-the-one-and-only-ivan">The One and Only Ivan&lt;/a>
by Katherine Applegate&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/3.Harry_Potter_and_the_Sorcerer_s_Stone">Harry Potter and the Sorcerer&amp;rsquo;s Stone&lt;/a>
by J.K. Rowling&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/6660638-silver-on-the-tree">Silver on the Tree&lt;/a>
by Susan Cooper&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/89724.We_Have_Always_Lived_in_the_Castle">We Have Always Lived in the Castle&lt;/a>
by Shirley Jackson&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/8520610-quiet">Quiet: The Power of Introverts in a World That Can&amp;rsquo;t Stop Talking&lt;/a>
by Susan Cain&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25521028-those-of-my-kind">Those of My Kind&lt;/a>
by &lt;a href="http://jennifertloring.com/">Jennifer Loring&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/15881.Harry_Potter_and_the_Chamber_of_Secrets">Harry Potter and the Chamber of Secrets&lt;/a>
by J.K. Rowling&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18702682-habeas-corpse">Habeas Corpse&lt;/a>
by &lt;a href="http://nikkihopeman.com/">Nikki Hopeman&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/5598017-the-little-stranger">The Little Stranger&lt;/a>
by Sarah Waters&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/14201.Jonathan_Strange_Mr_Norrell">Jonathan Strange &amp;amp; Mr Norrell&lt;/a>
by Susanna Clarke&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/5.Harry_Potter_and_the_Prisoner_of_Azkaban">Harry Potter and the Prisoner of Azkaban&lt;/a>
by J.K. Rowling&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18007535-the-winter-people">The Winter People&lt;/a>
by Jennifer McMahon&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>This is important. Not ground-shaking, earth-moving, sphincter-irritating
important, but important nonetheless.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Getting Back Into It</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2016/01/10/getting-back-into-it/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2016/01/10/getting-back-into-it/</guid><description>&lt;p>Nearly four years ago, in early 2012, I started taking Taekwondo. I was
overweight, out of shape, but my oldest minion had been taking classes for a
year plus and had just turned old enough to start doing family classes. So I
buckled down, drank plenty of water, tried not to smoke so much and gave it a
shot.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I didn&amp;rsquo;t just show up to class with him one day, though. The last thing I wanted
was for my son to see his old man collapse in a fit of coughing or pass out from
exhaustion or wind up twisting himself into so many Gordian knots even the EMTs
wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be able to save him. I took adult classes for a few months to get a
bead on where I really stood physically. Turned out I wasn&amp;rsquo;t in all that bad of
shape. Also, apparently very few folks actually went to the adult classes, so I
wound up getting a bunch of private lessons at regular cost and getting to know
the masters pretty well.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Sweet Baby Cthulhu! I've Been Infected!</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/10/23/sweet-baby-cthulhu-ive-been-infected/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2012 22:46:32 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/10/23/sweet-baby-cthulhu-ive-been-infected/</guid><description>&lt;p>The hip and talented writer
&lt;a href="http://joinmeinthemadhouse.blogspot.com/2012/10/author-infection.html">Stephanie Wytovich&lt;/a>
tagged me in a game of author infection. The rules are simple. Search your work
in progress for the first use of “look”. Copy and paste that paragraph and the
ones immediately before and after into a blog post. Then, like all good chain
letters, tag five other authors. Wash, rinse, repeat.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is from the nearly finished first draft of my novel &lt;em>The Galvanized Man&lt;/em>.
What kind of novel, you ask? I once described it as squishing Lovecraft and J.J.
Abrams into a dark post-apocalyptic cult fantasy. Yeah, I guess that works.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Look, Ma, No Word Processor!</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/10/20/look-ma-no-word-processor/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Oct 2012 10:15:05 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/10/20/look-ma-no-word-processor/</guid><description>&lt;p>A couple of weeks ago I posted about how I needed to get back to planning. My
current project—a novel that’s probably too complex, but fun to write—stalled
and I couldn’t find a way back into the story. I needed to put the word
processor aside and revisit the fundamental structure of the story.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I also mentioned in that post how I like to use index cards for planning my DIY
projects around the house. (By the way, the closet organizer we were working on
only needs a couple of coats of polyurethane and we’re done!) Index cards are
relatively portable, they constrain and force me to think about what I need to
capture, and I can easily rearrange them to change the structure of whatever I’m
working on.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>No More Sleepy Posts</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/10/11/no-more-sleepy-posts/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2012 06:05:55 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/10/11/no-more-sleepy-posts/</guid><description>&lt;p>Just a quick announcement I no longer plan to blog regularly about my polyphasic
sleep. I have a few different reasons, but the biggest is that frankly I don’t
think my personal experiment is all that interesting. I’m still interested, but
I can’t get all that excited about it. My sleep data goes back to the middle of
July, and what I noticed is that even when I sleep in, I usually only sleep
about six hours. I didn’t need much sleep to begin with, so I don’t see how I
can keep this interesting. My experiment will continue, and I may occasionally
bring it up in posts, but there’s just not enough material to keep my own
interest let alone someone else’s.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A Little Bit of Planning...</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/10/08/a-little-bit-of-planning/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2012 04:59:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/10/08/a-little-bit-of-planning/</guid><description>&lt;p>I had an epiphany yesterday while working on a “weekend project” that’s taken
several months. You see, there are no more real weekend projects in our home
since we had our second son. My wife and I are lucky to get five minutes to
ourselves on any given day, which is more than fine since we love our boys and
love hanging out with them. But it sure makes it tough to indulge our DIY
tendencies. For the past few months we’ve been converting the closet in our
front hallway from they typical sliding-door, hide-yer-shit closet to a built-in
locker. We’re doing this because when given a place to hide stuff, we will fill
it with all kinds of unnecessary stuff. It clutters our lives, weighs us down
and leaves us feeling overrun by… well, stuff.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Sleeping Like an Idiot: Week 7 - Charts!</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/09/24/sleeping-like-an-idiot-week-7-charts/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2012 03:33:40 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/09/24/sleeping-like-an-idiot-week-7-charts/</guid><description>&lt;p>I managed to pull together four charts to help demonstrate progress. I took a
cue from &lt;a href="http://www.fourmilab.ch/hackdiet/">The Hacker’s Diet&lt;/a> and used a
20-Day moving average to get trends. In each chart the actual measure is in blue
and the trend is in orange. For now I just used a Simple Moving Average since
the charts are just to get a sense of how things are going and aren’t meant to
give highly accurate measures.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Sleep Experiment: Week 6</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/09/18/sleep-experiment-week-6/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Sep 2012 07:28:56 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/09/18/sleep-experiment-week-6/</guid><description>&lt;p>I’m a couple of days behind in putting this up, mainly because I was hoping to
get some charts put together from my Zeo. The charts provided through its
software are nice, but they’re not really showing what I want, so I have a
little bit of work to do still.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Remember, I’m doing an Everyman sleep schedule, which involves a major sleep
event at night and multiple naps during the day. So far, on any given day I’m
down to a total of 5:30 hours of sleep. I’m doing this in part to make more time
for writing, and so far the writing’s going well.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Reintroducing the Sleep Experiment: 5 Weeks @ 5 Hours a Night</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/09/09/reintroducing-the-sleep-experiment-5-weeks-5/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2012 08:42:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/09/09/reintroducing-the-sleep-experiment-5-weeks-5/</guid><description>&lt;p>About five weeks ago I posted about the sleep experiment I was undertaking. I
haven’t been as diligent as I would like in recording results via blog, so I’m
going to do some catching up here and make the effort more frequently.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Yesterday I caught up on the progress of
&lt;a href="http://handyandypandy.com/polyphasic-sleep/">Handy Andy Pandy&lt;/a>—this dude’s an
inspiration for me. I also reread my [first
post]({% post_url 2012-07-21-a-writers-experiment-with-sleep %}) and realized it
didn’t actually share details on what I’m doing very well. I’m betting I was
still pretty foggy from my new sleep schedule.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>How to Succeed as a Writer</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/08/10/how-to-succeed-as-a-writer/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Aug 2012 06:45:51 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/08/10/how-to-succeed-as-a-writer/</guid><description>&lt;p>A couple of days ago, Jeff VanderMeer posted an articulate and insightful piece
&lt;a href="http://www.jeffvandermeer.com/2012/08/06/dreaming-well-does-the-future-of-publishing-need-more-imagination/">on the future of publishing&lt;/a>.
It’s not typical among the current flood of posts and opinions about where we’re
going or what the next hot thing is. Rather, Jeff gets to the heart of what he
believes to be a real problem today with the advice and predictions being touted
in the writing community.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Go read his
&lt;a href="http://www.jeffvandermeer.com/2012/08/06/dreaming-well-does-the-future-of-publishing-need-more-imagination/">post&lt;/a>
if you haven’t already.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A Writer's Experiment with Sleep</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/07/21/a-writers-experiment-with-sleep/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Jul 2012 16:56:04 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2012/07/21/a-writers-experiment-with-sleep/</guid><description>&lt;p>Last week I started a new experiment in writing, one that I hope will both boost
productivity and creativity. It’s not your typical experiment, though. I’m not
going to stand on my head while I write, or use prompt cards, or any other fancy
tools I don’t already use. I’m going to change something much more fundamental
about my writing habit. I’m changing my sleep. Okay, not so exciting, but I
think it’s a promising approach. You see, I’m already fairly comfortable with my
writing. It’s not perfect, but it’s workable and I think I’m at a point where
the best thing I can do to improve is to simply keep writing. I’ve done the
workshops, I graduated from Seton Hill’s awesome Writing Popular Fiction
graduate program, and I have a trusted group of critique partners and beta
readers. And I’m reading, something I always did but now I select what I read
with more intent on developing a sense of the genres I work in. What’s left?
Well, it’s just a matter of time. Something we’re all a little short on. I’m
determined to reduce the number of hours I spend in bed—sleeping, that is. We
all want more hours in the day, and I think it’s possible. We spend something
like 8 hours in bed each night, 1/3 of our day, and I’m not so sure it’s
necessary. A couple years ago, after having our second child, I embarked on a
similar journey. Everyone knows that having a kid is typically an exercise in
sleep deprivation, so I picked up this thing called a WakeMate to help me track
how much sleep I was getting. I’m not going to review it, but suffice to say the
thing wasn’t for me. In retrospect I should have realized I wouldn’t like it—I
hate wearing watches or anything on my wrist for that matter. So I used it for a
few months then gave up. Recently I came across a new device, the Zeo Sleep
Manager Pro+, and so far it’s awesome. It’s a headband instead of a wristband,
works with my iPhone, and gives pretty good stats on my sleep. I’m still trying
to figure out how I can share graphs and such. When I do, I’ll start posting
them here. Where am I going with this? I’ve always hated sleeping. Not the
actual act, but having to lie in bed for 8 hours straight. Don’t get me wrong, I
can and do sleep for that long, but somehow I always feel cheated out of time.
And after using the Zeo for a few days I’m beginning to see a reason for this
feeling (or maybe I’m rationalizing, but whatever). Zeo breaks your sleep down
into 4 catagories: Wake, REM, Light, and Deep.What’s interesting is that Zeo
discounts your time in Light Sleep. Wake, REM, and Deep all contribute to how
well you slept on any given night, but time in Light Sleep seems to make little
to no difference. Before using this thing, I would typically sleep six or seven
hours a night. And even though I would get up pretty early to write, lately my
writing’s been a struggle. This past week, I tried sleeping only five hours a
night with two 20-minute power naps during the day. So far so good. My
productivity was stellar (for me), with two days @ 1500 words, and the rest
@ 1000. On Friday, I let myself get a ‘normal’ night’s sleep (for me, that’s six
hours), and according to Zeo I slept better than most men my age can in eight
hours, with serious amounts of time in both REM and Deep sleep. And I felt great
in the morning. I’m not going to turn this into a sleep blog, but I will
periodically post things about my progress. My next goal is to figure out how to
share charts so you can actually see more details. Why am I sharing this? I
think too often when we struggle in our endeavors, be it writing or anything
else, we often overlook that possibility that changing something outside that
endeavor may help things improve. We, like the universe, are a complex
interaction of events and experiences. For me, writing is intimately connected
to my dreaming and sleep, and so I’m chasing the theory that altering something
in one will affect the other. My next experiment will deal with lucid dreaming.
But it’ll have to wait for two things: I reach a comfortable compressed sleeping
pattern, and the remee is released.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>