<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Shu_journal on David L. Day</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/categories/shu_journal/</link><description>Recent content in Shu_journal on David L. Day</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.davidlday.com/categories/shu_journal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Time for a Change</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2011/07/06/time-for-a-change/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2011/07/06/time-for-a-change/</guid><description>For the past two years, I used this blog to publish most of my reading journals for my graduate program. I graduated in June, and now it&amp;rsquo;s time to give this place a new purpose.
I&amp;rsquo;ve put a lot of thought into what kind of thing this site should morph into, and I haven&amp;rsquo;t quite decided yet. I think I&amp;rsquo;ll start doing book reviews, but we&amp;rsquo;ll see. For now, I&amp;rsquo;ll post the occasional thought and progress as I work toward publication.</description></item><item><title>Thoughts on The Exorcist by William Peter Blatty</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/10/17/thoughts-on-the-exorcist-by-william-peter-blatty/</link><pubDate>Sun, 17 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/10/17/thoughts-on-the-exorcist-by-william-peter-blatty/</guid><description>Most people should be familiar with Blatty&amp;rsquo;s The Exorcist by now. I mean, it&amp;rsquo;s a classic, right? The mere mention of the title suggests Linda Blair spewing ungodly amounts of pea soup. So no introduction is necessary. It is definitely a great horror novel that everyone with even a minor interest in horror should read. Go read it. Now. I mean it.
Okay, all due praise aside, there are two things about the novel that stood out for me as a writer.</description></item><item><title>Thoughts on Ansen Dibell’s “Plot”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/09/28/thoughts-on-ansen-dibells-plot/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/09/28/thoughts-on-ansen-dibells-plot/</guid><description>One of the most challenging things I struggle with as both a writer of fiction and a student of literature (yeah, they always go together) is which tool to use when. I believe that while reading and writing are intricately related&amp;ndash;you must be well-read to be well-written&amp;ndash;they don&amp;rsquo;t use the same mental tools.
The term plot (my archenemy when it comes to writing) appears in both toolkits, and I think that is terribly confusing.</description></item><item><title>Thoughts on Nate Kenyon’s “Sparrow Rock”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/08/24/thoughts-on-nate-kenyons-sparrow-rock/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/08/24/thoughts-on-nate-kenyons-sparrow-rock/</guid><description>I just finished reading Nate Kenyon&amp;rsquo;s latest novel, Sparrow Rock, a story of a group of high school kids who find themselves trapped in a bomb shelter by accident just as the end of the world arrives. Read the official synopsis from Nate&amp;rsquo;s site.
The novel has received excellent reviews at multiple sites, and I think the praise is well-deserved. Kenyon has produced a fast-paced, engaging tale of survival. This is the second book I&amp;rsquo;ve read by Kenyon.</description></item><item><title>Thoughts on Bently Little’s “The Town”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/08/08/thoughts-on-bently-littles-the-town/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/08/08/thoughts-on-bently-littles-the-town/</guid><description>Bently Little&amp;rsquo;s The Town was published in 2000, and I think even 10 years later it holds up as a good story. I found Bently&amp;rsquo;s take on small-town horror refreshing in many ways, even though the idea of horror in a small town isn&amp;rsquo;t so unique by today&amp;rsquo;s standards. The story involves a family of six who move back to the father&amp;rsquo;s home town after winning the lottery to simplify their lives and exchange the dangers of LA for the assumed tranquility of McGuane, Arizona.</description></item><item><title>Why Character Matters</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/07/05/why-character-matters/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/07/05/why-character-matters/</guid><description>I just finished reading Edward Lee&amp;rsquo;s The Golem. This is my first encounter with any of Edward Lee&amp;rsquo;s work. I believe every author should have two chances, so Ed Lee has one left. To me, the book read like a first draft, but I&amp;rsquo;ll get to that.
We don&amp;rsquo;t see the golem used much in popular fiction. I can only recall one instance where I&amp;rsquo;ve seen it used&amp;ndash;an old episode of the X-Files called Kaddish.</description></item><item><title>Manuscript Templates</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/06/09/manuscript-templates/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/06/09/manuscript-templates/</guid><description>Part of being a professional writer is ensuring your submissions meet format guidelines. William Shunn developed a set of format guidelines, originally published in December 1998 edition of Writers Write: The Internet Writing Journal. He also provides a set of templates on his site, but unfortunately they are only for WordPerfect. I use OpenOffice.
I decided to create my own templates based on his guidelines and offer them here for all to use.</description></item><item><title>One Helluva Ghost Story</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/04/27/one-helluva-ghost-story/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/04/27/one-helluva-ghost-story/</guid><description>I just finished reading Tom Piccirilli&amp;rsquo;s A Choir of Ill Children&amp;ndash;for the second time. I read it back in February and decided that to do it any justice, I needed to set it aside and reread it. It&amp;rsquo;s not an overly complex book, but I&amp;rsquo;m not used to the Southern style. The last book I read that felt stylistically similar was Faulkner&amp;rsquo;s As I Lay Dying&amp;ndash;over fifteen years ago.
The first thing that I noticed is the uniqueness of every character.</description></item><item><title>Another Round of How-To, Part 3</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/04/07/another-round-of-how-to-part-3/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/04/07/another-round-of-how-to-part-3/</guid><description>This is the last of a three-part journal on How to Write Tales of Horror, Fantasy &amp;amp; Science Fiction, Edited by J. N. Williamson, a collection of How-To articles by some of the best horror writers, circa 1987. Part one covered chapters 1-8; part two covered chapters 9-18.
The advice found in these final chapters still mirrors advice found in the wonderful On Writing Horror, another collection of How-To articles by some of horror&amp;rsquo;s best writers circa 2007.</description></item><item><title>Another Round of How-To, Part 2</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/03/23/another-round-of-how-to-part-2/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/03/23/another-round-of-how-to-part-2/</guid><description>This is part two of a three-part journal on How to Write Tales of Horror, Fantasy &amp;amp; Science Fiction, Edited by J. N. Williamson, a collection of How-To articles by some of the best horror writers, circa 1987. Part one covered chapters 1-8.
In my first post, I mentioned how strikingly similar the advice is to that found in On Writing Horror, another collection of How-To articles by some of horror&amp;rsquo;s best writers circa 2007.</description></item><item><title>Another Round of How-To</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/03/01/another-round-of-how-to/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/03/01/another-round-of-how-to/</guid><description>This is the first of three posts on How to Write Tales of Horror, Fantasy &amp;amp; Science Fiction, Edited by J. N. Williamson. The book is a collection of How-To articles by some of the best horror writers, circa 1987.
Late last year I did a series of posts on On Writing Horror, another collection of How-To articles by some of horror&amp;rsquo;s best writers circa 2007. Twenty years separate the publication of these two books, but so far I haven&amp;rsquo;t found anything other than the market survey that really differentiate the two.</description></item><item><title>Measuring Quality – Words or Pages</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/01/31/measuring-quality-words-or-pages/</link><pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/01/31/measuring-quality-words-or-pages/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;m a couple of weeks into my second term in Seton Hill&amp;rsquo;s MA WPF program. My thesis is a marketable horror novel, targeted at 350 pages. My personal goal is to complete the 1st draft by the end of this term, and spend the rest of my program editing and revision. Or rewriting if my mentors so command.
None of that is particularly interesting, but they&amp;rsquo;re facts that lay the groundwork for what&amp;rsquo;s been on my mind lately.</description></item><item><title>Back to work...</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/01/08/back-to-work/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2010/01/08/back-to-work/</guid><description>Just got back from residency orientation @ Seton Hill. It&amp;rsquo;s nice to be back, even if it meant driving 4 hours through snow. I had a great break, had a couple of good reads while I was off. First was John Scalzi&amp;rsquo;s Old Man&amp;rsquo;s War, a very entertaining science fiction book. It&amp;rsquo;s not my typical flavor, but it kept me reading, full of good action and interesting characters.
My other read was The Mammoth Book of Best New Horror, Volume 20, edited by Stephen Jones.</description></item><item><title>A Bit of a Break</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/12/01/a-bit-of-a-break/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/12/01/a-bit-of-a-break/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been on break from school since beginning of November, so I took the opportunity to brush up on mechanics. Specifically, I took a much-needed browse through the old Elements of Style. Good little book. But, I wanted more. So, I found a more contemporary take on style, Sin and Syntax, by Constance Hale. It&amp;rsquo;s longer than Elements. There&amp;rsquo;s plenty of praise for the book out in the wild; I&amp;rsquo;ll say I&amp;rsquo;m glad I took the time to read it as well.</description></item><item><title>Down to Business</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/21/down-to-business/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/21/down-to-business/</guid><description>In the end, writing is like any other endeavor. Sure, there is a significant and compelling creative aspect to it, almost mystical at times. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t just happen, though. The magic comes through sweat and rigor. King lays this out in his final section of On Writing.
His opinion is that there are 4 classes of writer: Bad, Competent, Good, and Genius. He states that there are 2 theses to his book:</description></item><item><title>Tools of the Trade</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/18/tools-of-the-trade/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/18/tools-of-the-trade/</guid><description>In part two of On Writing, King gives an overview of what he considers the essential tools for every writer&amp;rsquo;s toolbox. The analogy is interesting, and the story he provides at the start demonstrates an excellent point: Always have all your tools with you so you can tackle any unexpected situation.
So what goes in this metaphorical toolbox?
The first layer consists of common tools. The most common tool, per King, is vocabulary.</description></item><item><title>A Fogged-Out Landscape</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/17/a-fogged-out-landscape/</link><pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/17/a-fogged-out-landscape/</guid><description>It&amp;rsquo;s wonderful how much we can learn from stories, particularly when well told. Stephen King spends the first part of his book, On Writing, by walking the reader through a series of &amp;lsquo;fogged-out&amp;rsquo; memories. The book itself is about writing. But he sets the stage by doing what he does best, and tells the story of what made him what he is today.
I can&amp;rsquo;t say if it was intentional on his part, but in telling what he considers his &amp;ldquo;C.</description></item><item><title>“On Writing… oh, to hell with it.</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/15/on-writing-oh-to-hell-with-it/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2009 02:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/15/on-writing-oh-to-hell-with-it/</guid><description>The last section of &amp;ldquo;On Writing Horror&amp;rdquo; is all about the business aspect of being a writer. It provides a nice overview of the current markets, good resources for research and promotion, and some worthwhile advice from editors and writers alike.
Here&amp;rsquo;s the advice I&amp;rsquo;m taking right now, given by Night Shade Books:
Write what you think is your best book. Put it in a trunk and write another one. Do this four times.</description></item><item><title>“On Writing Horror” – Part Seven</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/15/on-writing-horror-part-7/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2009 00:01:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/15/on-writing-horror-part-7/</guid><description>Part 7 of On Writing Horror is titled &amp;ldquo;Genre and Subgenre&amp;rdquo;, but the 10 articles also cover concerns with medium as well (screenplay, theater, audio).
Archetypes and Fearful Allure: Writing Erotic Horror, Nancy Kilpatrick
I really struggled with this one. Kilpatrick seems to rely heavily on the concept of Archetypes, and the crux of her advice can be summed up in the following quote:
This means that the energy embedded in the image resonates with all readers because it taps into and stirs up the collective unconscious.</description></item><item><title>“On Writing Horror” – Part Six</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/11/on-writing-horror-part-six/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/11/on-writing-horror-part-six/</guid><description>Part 6 of On Writing Horror is titled &amp;ldquo;Tradition and Modern Times&amp;rdquo;, a series of articles covering horror tradition and its place in our modern literature.
No More Silver Mirrors: The Monster in Our Times, Karen E. Taylor
Taylor addresses how the old monsters can be made new again. She&amp;rsquo;s got some good advice, and I&amp;rsquo;ll get to that in a second, but there&amp;rsquo;s something she says early on that is direct opposition to what at least one other author claims in this series of articles.</description></item><item><title>“On Writing Horror” – Part Five</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/09/on-writing-horror-part-five/</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/09/on-writing-horror-part-five/</guid><description>Part 5 of On Writing Horror is titled &amp;ldquo;Horror, Art, Innovation, Excellence&amp;rdquo;. Five articles. Actually, 4 articles and one interesting interview with Harlan Ellison.
Innovation in Horror, Jeanne Cavelos
I&amp;rsquo;m starting to see patterns of advice in these articles, even though they have different emphasis. Cavelos talks in terms of innovation, but starts with the foundational advice of read a lot, read both in and out of the genre. Doing so helps the amateur writer avoid writing something that&amp;rsquo;s old under the false belief that they&amp;rsquo;ve written something new.</description></item><item><title>“On Writing Horror” – Part Four</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/07/on-writing-horror-part-four/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/07/on-writing-horror-part-four/</guid><description>Part 4 of On Writing Horror is titled &amp;ldquo;Horror Crafting&amp;rdquo;, and encompasses 7 articles on the craft. So many articles, and much of it is advice I&amp;rsquo;ve heard before, so I&amp;rsquo;m going to keep this as short as I can.
Such Horrible People, Tina Jens
Per Jens, &amp;ldquo;Horror is about how people react when they encounter the plot.&amp;rdquo; So to have good horror, we need good characters who interact with the plot.</description></item><item><title>“On Writing Horror” – Part Three</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/04/on-writing-horror-part-three/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/04/on-writing-horror-part-three/</guid><description>Part 3 of On Writing Horror is titled &amp;ldquo;Developing Horror Concepts&amp;rdquo;. It contains four articles dealing with conceiving and developing ideas for horror.
A World of Dark and Disturbing Ideas, J. N. Williamson
Williamson chooses to speak in terms of &amp;ldquo;useful premise&amp;rdquo; as opposed to &amp;ldquo;idea&amp;rdquo;, and I can appreciate his working definition. Idea&amp;rsquo;s are great, but they are largely useless if they cannot or will not be executed. This is true pretty much regardless of profession or circumstance.</description></item><item><title>“On Writing Horror” – Part Two</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/03/on-writing-horror-part-two/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/03/on-writing-horror-part-two/</guid><description>Part 2 of On Writing Horror, titled &amp;ldquo;An Education in Horror&amp;rdquo;, briefly addresses a horror writer&amp;rsquo;s education in four articles.
What You Are Meant to Know: Twenty-One Horror Classics, Robert Weinberg
Weinberg&amp;rsquo;s message is pretty clear - know your genre. He suggests that, in order to be marketable, you must be original. And, in order to be original, you must know what&amp;rsquo;s already been done. Aside from the mechanics of writing, a horror writer must be familiar with what&amp;rsquo;s been done.</description></item><item><title>“On Writing Horror” – Part One</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/01/on-writing-horror-part-one/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/10/01/on-writing-horror-part-one/</guid><description>Today I&amp;rsquo;m starting my journal entries for On Writing Horror, A Handbook by The Horror Writer&amp;rsquo;s Association. The book contains about 50 individual articles, divided among 8 different sections, so I&amp;rsquo;m going to match my entries up to the sections rather than address the articles individually.
Part one is called &amp;ldquo;Horror, Literature, and Horror Literature&amp;rdquo;. The three articles in this section seem to address whether Horror Fiction is or isn&amp;rsquo;t Literary Fiction.</description></item><item><title>“Urban Gothic” – No Signal</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/29/urban-gothic-no-signal/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/29/urban-gothic-no-signal/</guid><description>Screenwriter John August has an interesting little post on cell phones in the movies. It includes a great little montage of movie clips showing phones not working, getting smashed, etc. Why on earth do I care?
Brian Keene has this very problem in Urban Gothic. In an era where it seems everyone has a cell phone, how does a writer deal with it?
By my count, there are six teenagers in Keene&amp;rsquo;s book, each of whom has their own cell phone.</description></item><item><title>“Urban Gothic” and The Minotaur</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/24/urban-gothic-and-the-minotaur/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2009 00:02:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/24/urban-gothic-and-the-minotaur/</guid><description>Brian Keene’s recently released Urban Gothic brought to mind the myth of the Minotaur. A group of teens is thrown into a labyrinthine house whose twists and turns extend far below the ground in a neglected neighborhood. Their first encounter is with a hulking, deformed creature whose strength seems insurmountable.
Keene tells this story from multiple points of view, and I think that worked really well for the fast-paced action. I noticed, too, that Keene give the reader an immediate indication of POV change by having the POV character identified, in most cases, in the first sentence of any section change.</description></item><item><title>“Stephen King&amp;#58; The Art of Darkness” - Night Journey</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/24/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-night-journey/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2009 00:01:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/24/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-night-journey/</guid><description>What is the “night journey” in the context of Stephen King?
First, Winter shows how all of King’s works deal with some sort of journey. The idea of story as a journey is not new. Joseph Campbell is well known for his “Hero’s Journey”, and I’ve often encountered the aphorism that “the main character must change” (which is essentially an internal journey - A to B).
What I find most interesting is how Winter chooses to discuss the idea of journey in King’s works.</description></item><item><title>“Stephen King&amp;#58; The Art of Darkness” – Change of Approach</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/16/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-change-of-approach/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/16/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-change-of-approach/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;m scrapping the chapter-by-chapter approach for my discussion on Douglas Winter&amp;rsquo;s book.
Instead, I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to do a series of posts, each of which discusses what I found to be the most critical and relevant elements in Winter&amp;rsquo;s analysis. Here&amp;rsquo;s a list of topics I expect to cover. I&amp;rsquo;ll be spending no more than 30 minutes on any given element to keep myself from rambling on.
The &amp;ldquo;Night Journey&amp;rdquo; (East to West) The Haunted House Character growth from innocence to experience (tied to the &amp;ldquo;Night Journey&amp;rdquo;) The corruption of Fairy Tale Vision and the writing process That said, look for my first post in the next day or so.</description></item><item><title>“Stephen King&amp;#58; The Art of Darkness” (Ch. 3 – 4)</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/08/05/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-ch-3-4/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/08/05/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-ch-3-4/</guid><description>Chapter 3 - Carrie
In chapter 3, Winter begins his critical analysis of King&amp;rsquo;s work with Carrie.
Here&amp;rsquo;s what I took from this chapter:
Winter considers Carrie to be King&amp;rsquo;s most eccentric work. In part, it seems, due to the epistolary structure. Right from the start, King&amp;rsquo;s trademarks of &amp;ldquo;unassuming prose and truthful characterizations&amp;rdquo; are present. In King&amp;rsquo;s own words, he&amp;rsquo;ll go for terror, horror, and even the gross-out. Per Winter, Carrie &amp;ldquo;evokes the visceral, bringing the reader down to the guy level at which King operates best.</description></item><item><title>“Stephen King: The Art of Darkness” (Ch. 1-2)</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/29/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-ch-1-2/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/29/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-ch-1-2/</guid><description>The next book in my reading journal is &amp;ldquo;Stephen King: The Art of Darkness&amp;rdquo;, by Douglas E. Winter. Winter&amp;rsquo;s book is a critical look at King&amp;rsquo;s work up to the mid-80&amp;rsquo;s mixed with biographical information.
Chapter 1 - Introduction: Do the Dead Sing?
The first chapter and introduction to the work poses the question, &amp;ldquo;Do the Dead Sing?&amp;rdquo;. With that question, Winter brings us into the world of King by a broad overview of some of King&amp;rsquo;s works, and an analysis of how they fit into and have molded modern American Horror.</description></item><item><title>“From Shadowed Places”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/23/from-shadowed-places/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/23/from-shadowed-places/</guid><description>There are two aspects of this piece I find as valuable models for a writer. The first is the idea of death by inches. In my experience with horror, death come as a relatively swift blow - maybe there&amp;rsquo;s some torture, definitely some pain, but it is usually played out by a lot of tension and a quick end. Peter Lang has been under severe torture for months by the time we enter the story, and it shows through Matheson&amp;rsquo;s use of action, dialog, and description:</description></item><item><title>“Person to Person”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/22/person-to-person/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/22/person-to-person/</guid><description>Dialog like this is a challenge. Matheson&amp;rsquo;s main character, David Millman, is ultimately having a conversation with himself. He&amp;rsquo;s the crazy guy who hears voices in his head. I&amp;rsquo;ve written a couple of pieces that have this happen in them, but I haven&amp;rsquo;t been able to pull them off so well (in my humble opinion). Why is it that this story works but my own efforts haven&amp;rsquo;t?
I think it&amp;rsquo;s because when I&amp;rsquo;ve done it, my crazy main character sounds&amp;hellip; crazy.</description></item><item><title>“The Funeral”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/21/the-funeral/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/21/the-funeral/</guid><description>What I found most useful in this story is the sense of perspective, and how the POV character needn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily be the main character. The story is told from Morton Silkline&amp;rsquo;s perspective - the Director of a little cut-rate funeral home. While the story is his, I would argue that he doesn&amp;rsquo;t really experience any change and isn&amp;rsquo;t really the main character. It&amp;rsquo;s the vampire Ludwig Asper who is looking for a change, and ultimately receives it in the form of the funeral he never had.</description></item><item><title>“Mad House”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/18/mad-house/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/18/mad-house/</guid><description>Matheson uses a great focus technique to bring the reader into this story. The first four sections of &amp;ldquo;Mad House&amp;rdquo; are told in present tense, after which the story switches to the usual past tense. These first four sections, which cover only a few pages, are very special. They are tightly focused on the main character and his anger problem. They are very action oriented, walking the reader through several incidents of conflict between the main character and his surroundings.</description></item><item><title>“Dress of White Silk”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/15/dress-of-white-silk/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/15/dress-of-white-silk/</guid><description>Telling a story from a child&amp;rsquo;s point of view is a challenge. Telling it in a child&amp;rsquo;s language is a challenge as well. This piece was a little difficult for me to get engaged with because of Matheson&amp;rsquo;s lack of punctuation and the poor grammar (both intentional). This has the feel of an experimental piece.
I think that to be an effective writer at this sort of thing takes a lot of practice.</description></item><item><title>“Witch War”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/14/witch-war/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2009 00:02:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/14/witch-war/</guid><description>Why didn&amp;rsquo;t someone tell me there were so many vignette&amp;rsquo;s in &amp;ldquo;I Am Legend&amp;rdquo;?
Anyhow, this little snippet is almost poetry. It&amp;rsquo;s a great collection of images given in clear, if abrupt, language:
Sky clearing its throat with thunder, picking and dropping long lightening from immeasurable shoulders. Rain hushing the world, bowing the trees, pocking earth. Square building, low, with one wall plastic.
It&amp;rsquo;s what really stands out to me here.</description></item><item><title>“Prey”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/14/prey/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2009 00:01:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/14/prey/</guid><description>This vignette by Matheson gives an interesting parallel between a horrible little Zuni fetish doll, and the power of a parent over their child. As a reader, I enjoyed the chase and suspense of the woman being hunted by this little hunter. It&amp;rsquo;s a cool little encounter.
What I found most valuable as a writer, though, is the phone conversation between mother and daughter, as well as their family dynamic. Mother is manipulative and demanding, and is preying on her daughter&amp;rsquo;s emotions.</description></item><item><title>Undead Blog</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/11/undead-blog/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2009 00:04:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/11/undead-blog/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve revived my blog. It&amp;rsquo;s been dead for about a year. Poor blog.
I started a Master of Arts program in Writing Popular Fiction at Seton Hill University at the end of June. Kismet - the first day of my first writer&amp;rsquo;s residency was also my birthday.
Anyhow, part of the program involves reading (of course). And that requires a reading journal. Perfect use for a blog.
Welcome back, poor little neglected blog.</description></item><item><title>“The Near Departed”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/11/the-near-departed/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2009 00:03:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/11/the-near-departed/</guid><description>Another interesting little vignette by Matheson. To be honest, though, I didn&amp;rsquo;t find anything particularly interesting from a writer&amp;rsquo;s perspective. The dialog is plain, there&amp;rsquo;s little action, no real sense of tension, and the ending is standard &amp;ldquo;Twilight Zone&amp;rdquo; material.</description></item><item><title>“I Am Legend” (Ch. 17 – 21)</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/11/i-am-legend-ch-17-21/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2009 00:02:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/11/i-am-legend-ch-17-21/</guid><description>These are the final chapters. Matheson does a great job of continuing to create change in Neville. He&amp;rsquo;s encountered another human who is apparently immune as well, Ruth. He&amp;rsquo;s cold and distrustful at first, now having been in isolation for about 3 years.
He suddenly realized that he had become an ill-tempered and inveterate bachelor again. He no longer thought about his wife, his child, his past life. The present was enough.</description></item><item><title>“Buried Talents”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/11/buried-talents/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2009 00:01:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/11/buried-talents/</guid><description>This vignette by Richard Matheson presents an interesting technique for escalation. It&amp;rsquo;s brief story of an odd man who plays a game at the fair, the one where you chuck ping-pong balls into a fishbowl, and never misses.
The escalation is just that - the man never misses. It is, by nature of the scene, repetitive, but it&amp;rsquo;s the repetition of the man&amp;rsquo;s success that builds the story, bringing the reader along.</description></item><item><title>“I Am Legend” (Ch. 12 – 16)</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/09/i-am-legend-ch-12-16/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/09/i-am-legend-ch-12-16/</guid><description>Here we find Neville hitting another brick wall. He thinks he&amp;rsquo;s figured out what&amp;rsquo;s causing the vampires - a Bacilli (germ) - but he can&amp;rsquo;t attribute all the vampire behaviors to it. So, what does he do? Well, by this point we know Neville pretty well - a man who, although he&amp;rsquo;s survived some pretty extreme circumstances, falls back to the drink when things get too challenging.
Man, it&amp;rsquo;s time this guy get a new tune.</description></item><item><title>“I Am Legend” (Ch. 9 – 11)</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/07/i-am-legend-ch-9-11/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/07/i-am-legend-ch-9-11/</guid><description>So here we get more of Neville&amp;rsquo;s backstory, the death of his wife, his determination to bury her instead of burn her, and the horror of her return as a vampire. It&amp;rsquo;s interesting, but what really interested me more in these chapters is how Matheson shows us real change in Neville.
Neville has continued sobering himself up, tackling his situation like a real problem solver. He refers a few time to his father&amp;rsquo;s belief in the scientific method as inspiration.</description></item><item><title>“I Am Legend” (Ch. 4 – 8)</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/06/i-am-legend-ch-4-8/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/06/i-am-legend-ch-4-8/</guid><description>Matheson turns Neville&amp;rsquo;s character around in these chapters. At the end of chapter 4, Neville has forgotten to wind his watch and is stuck out after dark, not even sure what time it is. He survives the attacks, and spends the next couple of months rebuilding his home, getting to things he&amp;rsquo;d never done (like soundproofing the walls). He then sets about trying to figure out what he can about the virus or plague or whatever it is that&amp;rsquo;s caused all the people to turn.</description></item><item><title>“I Am Legend” (Ch. 1 – 3)</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/04/i-am-legend-chapt-1-3/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/04/i-am-legend-chapt-1-3/</guid><description>Matheson&amp;rsquo;s first three chapters do something I always find very difficult to pull off. He managed to develop a character in isolation, without having any benefit of dialog with another character. The description and narration combine well to bring out poor Robert Neville&amp;rsquo;s ordinary world.
I think Matheson also does a great job of building up the attackers through their actions (and the one who constantly taunts - &amp;ldquo;Come out, Neville!</description></item><item><title>“Dance of the Dead”</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/03/dance-of-the-dead/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/07/03/dance-of-the-dead/</guid><description>Richard Matheson&amp;rsquo;s short story, &amp;ldquo;Dance of the Dead&amp;rdquo;, is a fine example of matching up pacing and action. The story opens with four college kids racing across the plains in a &amp;ldquo;Rotor-Motors Convertible, Model C, 1997&amp;rdquo;. The kids are engaged in drinking, drugs, and sex as they head to Saint Louis to catch a &amp;ldquo;loopy&amp;rdquo; show.
Needle quivering at 130, two 5-mph notches from the gauge&amp;rsquo;s end. A sudden dip! Their young frames jolted and the thrown-up laughter of three was windswept into night.</description></item><item><title>“Stephen King&amp;#58; The Art of Darkness” – The Haunted House</title><link>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/28/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-the-haunted-house/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.davidlday.com/posts-archive/2009/09/28/stephen-king-the-art-of-darkness-the-haunted-house/</guid><description>Another element Winter discusses in his analysis of King is the haunted house. What strikes me as most interesting with this is that, while I think Winter does a good job of identifying the various &amp;lsquo;haunted houses&amp;rsquo; in King&amp;rsquo;s works, he never seems to talk about what the idea of &amp;lsquo;setting as character&amp;rsquo; directly.
For context, Winter identifies the following as noteworthy &amp;lsquo;haunted houses&amp;rsquo;:
The Martsen House in &amp;lsquo;Salem&amp;rsquo;s Lot The Overlook Hotel in The Shining The Agincourt Hotel in The Talisman The Dark Tower in The Dark Tower series * The last one is my own addition.</description></item></channel></rss>